[music]
>> Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome back to the Ask
video show. Today we discuss the world
of empires, kingdoms, and what is that
word? Vassals.
But before we do that, let me see who
all is there on the live chat. Let me
read some of you.
I can see
Ankita Kachhap, Himanshu Rajpurohit,
Meet Mystery 92 from Australia, Soumy
from Jaipur, Avinash 3174, Komal List,
Vikash PJ, good evening. Animesh
Bharatiya, Apex News Network from Assam.
Good to see you. History Go One, Udbhav
Sharma, Akuma T6N, Freedom from Outcome
from Canada. Good to see you, sir.
Sumit Namaskaram,
Swami Sudhir Kumar, Jai Shri Ram,
Bhaskar Bandit from Jaipur. Good to see
you. Meet Mystery,
Real Painter, Minimalist Maverick,
Sachin Yadav,
Adwait Ashwini,
Shankar Mahadevan, Darshan Patel,
Geopolitical Dubai from Indore. Good
evening.
Bhaskar Bandit once again, Minimalist
Maverick, Tanmay Deshpande, Crazy Brain.
Good evening. Dhairya from Jaipur. Good
to have you. Priyanka Jawalia, good
evening, ma'am. Lone Walker. Hello.
Soumya Dutta, good evening. McLovin69,
hello. Hello. Dr. Harsh
Dr. Harshita P. Naidu. Good evening.
Good evening.
Real Vladimir Putin is here.
Devnam Priya Priyadarshi from Odisha.
Jai Jagannath. Jai Jagannath. Harsha
Linga
Harsha Linga Utla. Okay, sorry.
Neil from Odisha. Gopinath Mishra, Komal
List once again, Gravity Good to see
you. Animesh Bharatiya,
Anindya Bhattacharya. Hello. Pranav 581,
Manisha Kardoso, Namaste Namaste. Sai
Nirup. Namaste. Dr. Dilli Nitish,
Boru Boruto Uchiha 5835. Good evening.
Devi Devika Shreyan. Hello. Animesh Paul
once again, Uncertainty Principle. Good
evening. Vikash PJ once again.
Deepika Mishra. Hello. Geopolitical
Dubai once again.
Uh Who else do we have?
Um
History Goal. Yes. You you you N4M.
Prathamesh Dinesh B18.
Ready always ready. All right, good to
see that. Ready always ready.
And Bhushan Bhushan Babar.
And everybody else. All right, good to
have you all. Author Santosh Rana is
also here from Odisha. Lots of people
from Odisha. Good to see that.
Um
Okay, so let's get going with some
questions. I'm going to take questions
about geopolitics and world affairs
today.
Sagar is here finding
Finding myself Shrishti Sap
Sapkota is here from Siliguri. Nice
place. Good to have you. Good to have
you, ma'am. Luffy Chan from Canada.
All right. I Yeah.
So let's take some questions. I'm going
to discuss geopolitics today, okay? So
please don't ask questions beyond from
beyond geopolitics. Today we discuss
geopolitics. Next week we're going to
take other
other topics as well. Maybe we'll do a
science special or maybe a space special
like people have been requesting. We can
do that. So let's what questions do we
have? I'll take questions from the super
chats first of all.
Bhaskar Bandit says Namaskaram. Hope
you're well. I'm well. I hope you're
well, too. Okay, what's the question?
Could you outline the civil war in
Sudan? Okay. Why is it geopolitically
crucial? Because of its close proximity
to the Suez Canal, global trade, or
natural resources, or more? What's the
deal?
This is a topic I haven't discussed thus
far, right? On
on this channel.
The The The civil war in Sudan. So I
could tell you
Okay, let's see how how it feels when I
say say it explain it this way. The
civil war in Sudan is a conflict between
the
RSF
and the Sudanese Armed Forces, SAF. The
RSF and the SAF.
The SAF is the government. The RSF are
kind of like rebels, and they are
fighting each other, and that's why we
have a civil war in Sudan. And both are
supported from by from external Both are
supported by external actors.
Does it make any sense what I just
explained? I threw around some words,
RSF, SAF.
They're fighting each other.
Does it make any sense? Now let me
explain it in a in a different way.
Hopefully it makes more sense. Let's go
to the map. As always, I must put the
map on the screen to explain the
context, okay?
Let's go to the map and understand what
hell what the hell is happening here.
We're discussing Sudan.
So if we are in India, we go westwards.
We cross the Sea of Saurashtra. We come
to the Horn of Africa, and we go further
west, and there we have Sudan. This
nation here in
the south of Sudan we have something
called South Sudan.
So what is the deal with this with this
region, this part of Africa?
So first of all, the broader context. If
we look at the northern regions of
Africa, these were historically
occupied, colonized, whatever you want
to call that.
They were historically occupied and
colonized by the Arabs,
which because of which in the northern
parts of Africa you will have primarily
Islamic or Muslim populations.
The southern parts of Africa, below the
Sahel region, south of the Sahel region,
you typically have more people who are
converted to Christianity by the
European occupiers, who occupied Africa
in the 18th, 19th, and 20th centuries,
and so on.
So the further south you go, the more
people you will find who are converted
to Christianity. Overall, very few
people
are left in Africa who still follow the
ancient African religions. It's mostly
Islam and Christianity. Northern
Northern parts of Africa you have Islam,
primarily Islam, and southern parts of
Africa you primarily have Christianity.
The dividing line is
kind of the the division the color
division here. You know, the desert
versus the green parts. Kind of roughly
kind of like that.
Now when it comes to Sudan. Okay, now
that we understand that, let's
understand the demographics of the
nation of Sudan.
The northern part of Sudan is primarily
Islamic, primarily Muslim populations.
The southern part of Sudan,
it's primarily non-Muslim. I would say
about 50-60% Christians, and the rest
would practice indigenous African
religions.
Right?
Now you can see that the capital city of
Sudan, Khartoum, is in the northern kind
of in the northern half of Sudan. If you
forget that South Sudan is a different
entity today, and if you see Sudan and
and South Sudan as as one single entity
like like it used to be,
then you will see that Khartoum is in
the north,
and because of that it's primarily
Islamic, okay?
Now,
so Sudan was ruled by the Ottomans, by
the Arabs, and so on. From the 19th
century onwards it was ruled by the
British,
the Egyptians as well.
And in the 20th century, until which
year was it? It was I think the year of
the Suez crisis, '56 was it?
Probably around 1956, until that time
you had the Egyptians and British
jointly ruling Sudan.
All right?
Now,
when Sudan became independent, most
likely in 1956, you can look up the
exact date, the exact year I mean.
So when Sudan became independent, there
was this conflict about who's going to
rule Sudan.
Is Sudan going to be an Islamic nation?
Is it going to be a secular nation? And
obviously the people in the north,
they wanted Sudan to be an Islamic
nation.
So the government that took
took over in Khartoum, in northern
Sudan,
they they imposed Sharia law on Sudan.
And because of that you had
mass protests and revolts and whatnot in
the south, because they did not want to
be under Sharia law. And that's why they
had you had civil war like situations,
and the northern the government of
Sudan, which was based out of the
northern part, the
out of Khartoum, they
used all kinds of nasty tactics to
to retain power.
Uh
So that was the situation in the 1950s,
all the way to the 1980s, civil war, and
lots of atrocities and whatnot.
In the 1980s and and there onwards, a
set of militias were empowered by the
government to
to oppress the people who did not want
Islamic rule, and so on. And these
militias were called the Janjaweed
militias. Janjaweed. I don't know what
it means. Whatever it means. Janjaweed.
And they
carried out all kinds of horrific
atrocities on the people of southern and
even even western Sudan. Darfur, the
Darfur region of Sudan, which is in the
western part of Sudan. So, eventually
South Sudan seceded in Sudan. You can
look up which year it happened.
Okay? But that's what happens.
And then, whatever is left of Sudan, is
still have a southern part in which you
have primarily non-Muslim people.
So,
in the 21st century from 2000
2 2003 onwards,
maybe 2005 onwards, whichever year it is
year it is, there is a terrible conflict
in Darfur in southern southern Sudan, in
which these Arabic
so-called Arabic militias called the
called the Janjaweed that I mentioned,
they
committed all kinds of horrific
atrocities, massacres, genocide,
whatever
on the people who did not want to be
under Islamic rule.
Uh maybe a couple of couple of million
people would have died, civilians
mainly. Okay?
So, that has been the situation. Now,
fast forward
to the 2010s. So, the Janjaweed, these
people who
identify as Arabs,
they are now transformed into something
called the RSF, Rapid Support Force,
which is a paramilitary force which is
in in alliance with the Sudanese Armed
Forces, the SAF.
Now, you understand SAF and RSF. So, the
RSF is the rebranded Janjaweed militias
consolidated together.
And they are kind of like an auxiliary
force at this point in time, 2010s
early.
They are kind of an auxiliary force to
the Sudanese Armed Forces. But then,
these two sides become competitors
eventually. Now, in 2019,
uh the president of of Sudan, his name
was Bash Bashir, whatever his name was,
he was ousted by the Sudanese Armed
Forces.
And
I'm not sure who's ruling Sudan right
now. Must be some general of some kind.
Okay? Doesn't matter who's ruling it.
It's the and And then, what you have is
that there is a conflict between the RSF
and the Sudanese Armed Forces.
Um the in 2019, 2020, maybe 2023 around
that time, there were talks to integrate
the two
the two forces, the RSF and the SAF,
into one single integrated integrated
unit. But there were too many
differences and there were too many
competing agendas. So, it did not work
out. And today, the civil war in Sudan
is a civil war between the Sudanese
Armed Forces and the Rapid Support
Forces. Now, it is alleged that the
Sudanese Armed Forces are supported by
certain external actors. And the RSF are
also supported by certain external
actors. And who's caught in between? It
is the innocent civilians who and there
is a
horrific uh humanitarian crisis in
Sudan. Now, why
would external actors support
the SAF or the RSF? Why?
And since 2023,
there's been this
you know, back and forth kind of battle
battles going on. The lines on the map
are like Pink Floyd would say, they move
from side to side, that sort of thing.
You know? At sometimes, Khartoum is in
the hands of the RSF, sometimes it's in
the hands of the SAF. That sort of
thing. It's going on back and forth.
But why would external actors
why would they support
one of the two forces in Sudan?
Well, the thing about Africa,
the fantastic thing about Africa,
is that it is so rich
in natural resources, mineral wealth.
If you talk about Sudan, what sort of
mineral wealth does it have?
The golden metal, gold.
There's plenty of gold in Sudan. And
whoever controls the land of Sudan
gets to extract the gold. So, it is
alleged that the Sudanese Armed Forces,
the SAF,
it is alleged that they are supported by
the United States and somebody else.
And it is alleged that the that the RSF
is supported by allegedly Russia and
allegedly some some specific Gulf
nation, allegedly. Okay? That's the
that's what is being said about this.
Uh so, the RSF today is said to be
slightly more secular than the SAF.
The Sudanese Armed Forces are purely
Islamist and the RSF are more Rapid
Support Forces are more pragmatic.
Uh but whatever it is, both are overall,
you could say,
they will bring Sharia law if they take
power. That's essentially the situation.
So, that is the civil war in Sudan. Now,
I hope it makes sense once I have put
the entire history in perspective.
Okay?
And it's all about control of resources
in the nation in Sudan. But that's the
deal in Africa. These African nations
are are sadly, tragically, today dirt
poor because of the couple of past
centuries of foreign occupation and
destruction.
So, these nations are dirt poor, but
they are tremendously wealthy in natural
resources. And that's what external
actors want.
And that's why they support
either militias or they support
dictatorships. So, you pay the dictator
a certain amount of money every year,
you give them some prestigious whatever
thing you you know,
some honors or whatever. You Yeah, that
sort of thing. And then,
if you do that, then they will be happy
to sell out their country parcel by
parcel to you. That's how it goes. So,
that is the deal.
And of course, it is kind of
the nation is kind of close to the Suez
Canal, but it's not about the Suez
Canal. It's about the natural resources
that Sudan has. So, who would like it?
Everybody would want it.
The US would want it, the Russians would
want it, maybe the Chinese would want
it. But who are the players involved?
It is alleged that it's it's the
Americans on one side and the Russians
on on another side. And other actors
also may or may not be involved,
allegedly.
That is the deal
about the civil war that's going on in
Sudan. It is a horrific humanitarian
situation, tragic,
and it's going on. And we don't know
what the outcome is going to be.
Right? That's the deal. Okay.
Hope that explains it.
WBR says, "In the operation spider web,
why did Ukraine avoid attacking the most
modern Tupolev 160 bomber?
Your opinion on Trump's latest peace
deal seen as a surrender of Ukraine to
Russia."
Okay, look, uh
did
Ukraine avoid attacking the most modern
bomber?
So, so they attacked two
um
military installations. One was, if I
recall correctly, it's been a while now,
uh
one was a naval installation somewhere
and there was one uh air base in which
many
Russian strategic bombers were were
damaged or destroyed. We don't know the
exact numbers. The Ukrainians
claimed 20 plus. The Russians said less,
whatever it is. I'm not sure what kind
of bombers were destroyed. Was it the
Tupolev the the
The Tupolev 160 is what? Is it the Bear?
Let me just check out very quickly.
Uh or is it the Swan, the White Swan?
There is the Bear, there's the White
Swan. I think the Tupolev 160 would be
the White Swan, right? Let me see.
TU-160.
Is this the White Swan? It is the White
Swan.
Is this the White Swan?
Uh is it the White Swan?
Tupolev 160.
Yeah, it's called the White Swan. Yes.
160.
And Tupolev Bear.
Tupolev 95. I think these are the ones.
Uh Tupolev 95 with the counter-rotating
propellers.
Probably these are
some of the bombers that were damaged or
dis and/or destroyed.
Uh why did they do this instead of that?
I'm not really sure. I don't know
which kind of bombers were targeted.
Maybe
maybe they they
the more modern ones are kept somewhere
else.
Maybe you can't hit everything
that you want to, right?
Uh you have limited resources, you have
limited
points of ingress into Russia, you have
you know, actors who are positioned
inside Russian territory. So, you can't
hit everything you want. I mean, why
didn't they hit Moscow also? You could
ask. So, they hit whatever they could.
And
it was definitely a pretty spectacular
operation and a significant success for
Ukraine. And it was kind of a major
embarrassment for Russia, not to mention
a military setback.
Right? So, that's the deal. I don't
really have an answer. It's
maybe they they did not have the
resources in in in position to attack
the Tupolev 160s.
Uh Trump's latest peace deal, surrender
of Ukraine to Russia? No,
[clears throat] it's pragmatic. Look,
I'm not sure what news you people watch.
I have been saying since February 2022
that Russia is winning.
And I have been ridiculed, right?
I have Lots of people have made fun of
me.
That Russia is losing, they've lost 7
million soldiers, they've lost this,
they've lost that. Putin has cancer,
Putin is dying in 3 months.
All kinds of propaganda. I have been
steadfast in what I have been saying.
Russia
is going to achieve its military and
political objectives in the Ukraine
conflict. Now, where are we?
This is the Trump's peace deal, right?
Is he Is he
actually surrendering Ukraine to Russia?
He's not surrendering the whole of
Ukraine to Russia. What what he is
proposing is that Russia gets to keep
whatever territories it has captured
from Ukraine.
And the whole of the Luhansk Donetsk
Donetsk oblasts.
And there is a you know, a ceasefire
line that will be drawn based on more or
less current
uh locations current
you know, positions on the map
of the Armed Forces. And furthermore,
Ukraine
gives an assurance as part of Trump's
deal that it will never become a part of
NATO
and probably more.
So, is this a surrender? No, it is a
recognition of the facts on the ground.
I don't know what news sources you read
from. Maybe these are Western news
sources you read from, you're observing,
which is why you get the impression that
you can
winning all the time and how come Trump
is surrendering everything? He's
surrendering nothing. He's simply
recognizing the reality, the ground
realities.
The longer this goes on, the more the
West will be drained, especially Europe.
It's better to freeze the conflict where
it is right now. Create a North
Korea-South Korea kind of situation.
Ukraine gets partitioned, like I've been
saying since February 2022. Ukraine will
be partitioned. Which line? Well, if if
uh Trump's current proposal is accepted,
then the current battle lines, that will
be the ceasefire line. That will be the
partition line. If uh
that is not accepted by the by the by
Zelenskyy and by the European vassals of
the US, well, then maybe the the Dnieper
River eventually becomes the ceasefire
line, which means Russia goes further
West. Maybe there's a regime change in
Kyiv, which anyway may happen.
If the if uh Trump's um peace deal or
proposal uh goes forward, right?
So, that's how I see it. It's not a
surrender. It's it's simply a
recognition of the ground realities. But
Russia is winning.
The West has been propagandizing all all
over the place, on social media, on
think tank articles and you know, BBC,
CNN, Fox, Deutsche, whatever. Everywhere
they have been propagandizing that
Russia is losing badly, Ukraine is
winning. Yeah, right.
So, it's simply a recognition of the
ground realities.
Pratik Powar says, "Why do people around
the West respect Russians? Is it really
due to the Second World War victory of
Russia or is is there another specific
reason?"
Well, that's a good question.
The people
People around the world respect
Russians. Yeah.
But people in the West, they don't like
Russia.
They many of the people in the West kind
of hate Russia. They see Russia as an
enemy.
But they respect Russia. Now, do you
understand a little bit of context? You
may dislike them, but you respect them.
Now, where does respect come from?
Does it come from admiration?
Respect doesn't necessarily come from
admiration. Especially when you dislike
the nation. You dislike the nation, but
you respect them. So, it's not
admiration that's bringing out the
respect.
It is fear.
At the basis of a lot of respect,
especially in geopolitics, there is
fear. Now, why is Russia feared?
Because Russia won't crumble.
Russia goes after its enemies.
Russia goes after the traitors who
betray Russia.
Have you heard of polonium?
Have you heard of the Litvinenko case
and
many other instances? Russia goes after
its traitors. Russia ensures that
justice is done.
Justice to the to the nation, justice to
Rossiya Matushka,
Mother Russia,
right?
Beyond that, Russia was
in a shambles 25 years ago. And today
look at Russia. It has climbed back on
its feet. It's resolute. It has a
fearsome military.
It has the world's largest nuclear
arsenal. It may not have
the most prestigious aircraft carrier
capabilities in the world, but that
doesn't matter. It has some of the
deadliest nuclear submarines in the
world.
Why is Russia Russia respected?
Because Russia doesn't take nonsense
from anyone.
Yeah? And nobody can bully Russia.
That's why Russia is respected. Russia
doesn't want to play the good boy.
Please like me, sir. Sir, please like
me.
Yeah? That's why Russia is is respected.
Now, ask yourself about some other
country. Maybe whatever your favorite
country is. Is it respected? If it is
not,
then why is it not respected? Whichever
your favorite country is, ask
yourselves.
Tanmay Deshpande says, "Is Russia
becoming the most successful revisionist
power of the 21st century after its
November gains?" Uh
November gains? Which November gains?
Are you talking about Ukraine?
The lines on the map on the map in
Ukraine have been kind of frozen for a
very long time.
Steady
situation. Maybe a couple of miles here
and there. I'm not sure what major
November gains have happened. If
something major would have happened, I
would have known about it. I don't
register small changes, uh
incremental changes,
um
or progress
in the Ukraine war. I register major
changes. So, I my radar is set for major
changes, major progress or regress or
whatever, but little a couple of
kilometers have been caught here or some
village was captured, I don't really
care about that. So, I'm not sure what
what gains happened in November. Now, is
Russia a revisionist power?
I would say a lot of Indians
they seek to regain
Pakistan-occupied Kashmir.
Us in some people in the West would call
it revisionism. You're trying to change
the lines on the map. You're trying to
rewrite history.
Some people in India want
what? Akhand Bharat.
And that could also be portrayed as
revisionism. China seeks to expand its
territory.
China seeks to
you know, take Taiwan. China China seeks
territory from India. China seeks
territory from Russia. Isn't that
revisionism?
So, these terms like revisionism,
revisionist power, etc., these are used
especially in the Western media to as as
as sticks to beat nation nations with.
Um so, I don't know about revisionist
power. Russia is simply looking out for
its for its best interests.
And what are Russia's best interests?
You don't want NATO on on your doorstep.
So, you deal with Ukraine in the way it
it has to be done. And that's what it's
doing.
And uh
how has the Ukraine campaign gone thus
far? I would say very successful.
Right? The it was known that the West
would unleash sanctions on Russia and
they have.
The United States, the Europeans, every
nation you could imagine, all the
vassals of the US came together and
unleashed every sanction you could
imagine on Russia and it did not have
the effect that that they had intended.
The intention was to destroy Russia,
crush Russia's economy.
What happened?
On the contrary, Russia's economy
actually grew. Grew to some extent,
right? It's not in recession. It's
actually growing. It's growing better
compared to the European economies.
Um
and Russia has not been isolated. It has
certain nations
on its side. Some are on Russia's side
because of convenience. Some are on
Russia's side because of other reasons,
whatever it is, right? So, Russia has
been successful thus far in the Ukraine
conflict. And the way things are going,
it looks like uh Trump
will sooner or later
insist and prevail upon you Ukraine to
accept a ceasefire proposal, which
has to be in Russia's favor because
Russia has the facts on the ground.
Russia has created facts on the ground
and those
you can
you can draw a map whichever way you
want, but you know what's there on the
ground, right? So, you have to recognize
that.
And yeah, so Russia is going to prevail
in the Ukraine conflict.
Uh so,
it's it's going to be successful. Now,
is it going to be the Is it Is it
becoming the most successful revisionist
power? I don't know. The 21st century,
uh
it's another 75 years years to go. Thus
far, uh Russia is doing a good deal of
standing up to the to the to the West
and we are witnessing the the
the emergence of Cold War 2.0,
uh which most likely will drag India
into it as well.
And it remains to be seen on which side
India goes.
Minimalist Maverick says, "It seems like
Russia is going all in in this war and
the West won't supply it won't stop
supplying arms to Ukraine.
Timeline-wise, if it drags till 2035."
See, Russia
There's this question that pops up all
the time, doesn't it? Why
is Russia playing the slow game
in the Ukraine war?
Why is it dragging out the conflict for
years?
Why is it happy with this frozen war
scenario?
Why is it happy with this slow war
You know, frozen battle lines, stagnant
battle lines.
Why doesn't it simply make a move on
move on Kyiv and finish it off, right?
So, that's one question that keeps
popping up. But
we know that the Russia has the military
capabilities required to do that. They
can flatten Ukraine tomorrow morning if
they want to.
But clearly they don't want to. And why
do they not want to? First of all, they
don't see the Ukrainians as foreign to
them. They see the Ukrainians as their
kin, Slavic people. And secondly, the
longer this war drags on, see, if you
end the war tomorrow, you take Kyiv, you
dethrone Zelenskyy, send him into exile,
hopefully,
whatever, and you partition Ukraine at
at a certain line, then the war ends.
And then, if the war ends, what happens?
The West has to stop supplying weapons,
arms, ammunition, money, funds, whatever
to Ukraine because Ukraine no longer
exists.
So, the financial drain on the West
ends.
But if the war goes on and the West
keeps on investing money
in
arms, ammunition, whatever the Ukraine's
need. So, it keeps on bleeding the West,
but you could argue it's also bleeding
Russia.
But you see, Russia is an autarky. And
this war has actually strengthened
Russia's industrial base, military base,
economic base.
It's had a very counter-intuitive effect
on Russia. It has strengthened Russia.
Russia is now a full-fledged war economy
and they are robust now.
Into Russia, you know, if you look at
historically how Russia has performed in
wars, initially in any war, they don't
perform well.
But give it a couple of years and then
see them
rebound.
Right? Initially, they don't do well,
but then they adapt.
They adapt. And they have the territory.
And they have the resources. And they
have whatever else is needed.
So, Russia has adapted and Russia is
doing well now.
So, um
So, the war will go on as long as it is
beneficial to Russia and that's why
Trump wants to end it soon.
Right? So, that it's the the So, it's
stops being such a such a drain on the
West.
Uh
So, how do I see this going? I I
I would say that the war will most
likely end in some kind of ceasefire
maybe in the next 6 to 12 months.
Trump will ensure if it happens because
see, first of all, it's a matter of
prestige for Trump also. He had promised
his voters that he will end the Ukraine
war on day one of his presidency.
And this has not happened. It makes him
look very bad. Trump doesn't like
looking bad.
So, he's going to make it happen.
And if Zelenskyy and the Europeans
insist on keeping the war going on, then
he will do something
about it.
Right?
So, I
the way I see it, the war should end in
the next 6 to 12 months.
It will end in some kind of ceasefire in
some kind of uh
ceasefire deal which will not be good
for Ukraine, but it will recognize the
realities on the ground.
And until the war ends, the West has no
option but to keep supplying arms,
weapons, fuel,
food supplies, humanitarian supplies,
fighter
fighter planes, whatever it fuel, etc.
to to Ukraine. And that's a big drain on
the Western economy. On the European
economy.
So,
I think it will end sooner rather than
later.
ICMBS
says, "Prime Minister heard my critique
about the education system that keeps us
in inferiority complex. How would you go
about changing it?"
Uh the Prime Minister has heard my
critique.
I recall
seeing some statement hearing about some
statement from the Prime Minister about
the Macaulay education system or
something.
Uh it's good to hear that, but what
action is being taken is the question.
I have been speaking about this
five, six, I don't know how many years.
As as as long as I have been a face in
the public domain, I have been speaking
about the Macaulay education system, how
it needs the colonial education system.
It needs to be reformed. I have it
I think three episodes of the Ask
Abhijit Show dedicated to the education
system and the need to reform the
education system and I have not only
pointed out the problems, which anybody
can, I've also given solutions, which
very few people do.
I've given very specific situations
solutions.
Are any of those solutions being
implemented is the question I would like
to ask.
There is something called the new
education policy.
The new education policy doesn't address
any of the
any of the fundamental defects, issues
in the in the education system. You can
revise some of the syllabus.
You can, you know, restructure the
education system in
some ways. It's a good start, but it's a
minor minor
change.
The deeper malaise still remains.
Right?
So, how would I go about changing the
education system? Once again, let me
show you all how I would do that.
Uh I will not explain it in detail right
now, but I will tell you
where to look for my explanation about
how to change the education system
because I have spoken about this in
great detail.
So, uh let me put that on the screen.
One second. Give me a second. So, you
can check out those episodes in which I
have spoken about this in great detail.
Give me a second. All right. So, this is
my channel. These are the This is the
live stream tab over here as you can
see. It was about episode 28, 29. See,
okay.
So, I have three episodes. Episode 28 of
Ask Abhijit, episode 30,
and episode 31. In these three episodes,
I have spoken in great detail about how
the education system is a disaster for
India, how it is it is keeping India
down, it is ruining ruining the future
of of the future generations of India,
of Indians, and what needs to be done to
fix this. Episodes 28,
30, and 31 of the Ask Abhijit Show, the
same show that you're watching right
now. This was about more than 4 years
ago that I spoke about it. And whatever
I spoke about whatever I said in those
episodes, it still is 100% relevant
today.
So, that's how I would go about changing
it. If you are interested, please watch
those episodes. Thank you, sir. Thank
you, ma'am.
Okay.
Uh WBR464
says, "Did you know Yevgeny Prigozhin
was a Jew?" I did not know that.
I'm not aware. Was he a Jew? If he was a
Jew, well, okay. Zelenskyy is also a
Jew. There are plenty of Jewish people
who are in prominent positions in the
West.
It is what it is. Yeah. So, I was not
aware what he's a Jew.
If you would like to If you would like
me to fact-check that, I can do that,
but
not sure how it is relevant. Yevgeny
Yevgeny Prigozhin No. Yevgeny
Prigozhin.
Oh, was he Jewish? This fine gentleman.
Let's see.
Open up.
Open up. All right. Let us see.
Uh
father was etc.
His father and stepfather are believed
to be of Jewish descent. So, it's
believed to be. We don't know for sure
and how does it really matter?
It's all right.
Okay.
Andy Butt says,
"Big fan. Thank you very much, Andy G.
Please throw some light on the recent
G20 summit. Did Mr. Modi go do good by
visiting it? I hope Donald Trump is not
angry tariff threat."
I haven't examined the G20 summit. See,
um just
FYI to everybody,
I don't I'm not
a news surfer.
I the way I examine the world, analyze
the world, is I do it not in real time.
I take my time. If something happens,
I'll wait for a week
for it to
for the thing to happen. Let's say
there's a summit, a major summit
happening somewhere. I will not be stuck
to the television screen watching the
latest news updates about what's
happening. I'll take my time. I'll wait
for a week for the summit after the
summit is done and then I will examine
what are the major outcomes of the
summit.
So, the summit has just happened, I
would say. Is it still on? I'm not sure
about that.
Uh so, I'm not even sure if it's on or
not.
And I know that Prime Minister Modi
attended the summit, obviously. And it
was in South Africa, if I recall. I
mean,
the images of Prime Minister Modi's
visit were all over social media. I
mean, even today I saw some of them. So,
it looks like it was it is still ongoing
or maybe it's just over. I'm not sure.
I'll take a week or so to
analyze what happened in the summit,
what came out of it, what was its
relevance for India,
and then we can discuss it.
Um
Right now, it's it's too early for me to
comment. Okay? But I will certainly
revisit this this matter.
Let's say in a week's time.
But uh did Mr. Modi do a good thing by
visiting
by attending the G20 summit? Well, yes.
India should attend these summits.
We hosted the G20, right? In 2023.
Just a couple of years ago.
Um
And one of the major things we did in
the 2023 summit was to make
the African Union
um member of the G20.
So, yeah. Nobody had bothered bothered
to do that until we did it.
Uh so, yeah, it is important for India
to
be present in these summits and
participate and take a leadership role
wherever applicable, relevant, and
possible.
And uh yeah, so it's a good thing that
Mr. Modi did attend the summit and
participate in it. I'm not sure about
Donald Trump whether he's angry or not.
Tariff threats? Yeah. Well, tariffs are
on, right?
And there's a 500% tariff threat also
that there is somewhere down the corner.
We'll see about that.
Minimalist Maverick says, "Explain
African and Latin American geopolitics
and who is whose vassals and business
opportunities. If possible, can you make
a 6-hour video on this?"
Well,
you gave me the You first gave me the
problem and then then gave me the
solution. See, if you want me to explain
African and Latin American geopolitics,
it will take me 6 hours.
Africa is the largest continent. Latin
America, South America is a gigantic
gigantic continent.
And to understand geopolitics, you have
to understand history. So, it's
impossible for me to explain in the next
5 minutes, even 15 minutes, the history,
the context
of just let's say African geopolitics
cuz there are so many factors, so many
players involved. When I just now the
first question I took was about the
conflict in Sudan, right? The civil war
in Sudan. That took me like 10 15
minutes to answer. And I even for that I
gave a very high-level overview of
what's been happening in Sudan.
So, you see it's
it will probably take me a 6-hour video
to explain all of that in detail.
But if I were to explain about the
vassalhood situation,
there is no major power in Africa.
They're all somebody or the other's
vassals.
There is again same way, there is no
major
geopolitical power in South America,
even Central America.
They are all somebody's vassals
either directly or indirectly. Who is
that somebody?
Well, it's definitely not Russia or
China. The Chinese are kind of involved
in Africa, definitely. Even the Russians
are. The Chinese are the money, the
Russians are the muscles.
Or the muscle. You have the Wagner Group
and then you have the evolution of the
Wagner Group. But whatever it is, it's
the same entity.
Or maybe a slightly evolved or modified
entity, whatever. So, you have Russia
and China involved in Africa
geopolitically because
uh they've got to be present there.
Africa is so rich in resources. And
why would they not want to partake of
that? Similarly, in South America also,
the Chinese have been uh
a
decent
not a decent, I'd say a robust player
actually the past 15 or so years.
And yeah, but overall if you look at
Latin America, it is under
uh you could say the domination, the
hegemony of the United States. The good
old Monroe Doctrine of the 19th century
still applies.
It is no longer fashionable to call it
the Monroe Doctrine because it sounds
outdated, but it is what it is. It still
applies.
And in Africa,
well,
the French were a major power for quite
some time, but now they have completely
withdrawn. And they have created a power
vacuum which the Russians will be happy
to exploit, even the Chinese.
But mainly, the major
major power in the in the in the
continent of Africa is still the United
States.
Okay.
Rithik Pawar says, "Why did Trump skip
the G20 summit? Is G2 a new world order
now?" I am not sure why Trump skipped
the G20 summit. Like I said a while ago,
uh I have not I'll take my time to
analyze what happened in the G20 summit.
I don't
uh surf the news in in real time.
Because you see, why
you may wonder, "Why do I not keep track
of what's happening in real-time?"
I mean, if I'm supposedly a geopolitical
analyst or whatever, then should I not
be staying in touch with what's
happening in the world? Or should I not
be interested in what's happening right
now? Isn't it important? Right?
You see, the the the the truth is
that the more you watch the news, the
less you know about what's happening in
the world.
99% of of the news is noise.
It's shouting. It's propaganda.
It's agenda setting. It's narrative
setting.
The more you spend your time watching
the news, the less you will understand
what's happening.
So, I don't watch the news. I take my
time and then I I have my sources of
where to obtain my information from.
And then I analyze it
calmly.
Right? So, I'm not a news surfer.
I'm going to take my time and I'm not
quite sure what Trump has decided about
the G20. Did he skip it? In case he
skipped it, why did he skip it?
I'll I'll look into that.
Is G2 a new world order right now?
Not quite.
Um it's still too early for a G2
situation.
It's more like a G4 G5 situation. Who
are the G4 G5? Well, you obviously have
the US and China, the two two major
economies. But China is not a
superpower, even if the US is trying to
position China as kind of a peer rival,
peer competitor.
China is nothing compared to the US,
especially in terms of military
capabilities and power projection
capabilities. Economically, it's kind of
reaching there, right? So, you have the
US and China, the G1 and G2, the two.
Then you have Russia, a major military
power, right?
The most powerful nuclear power in the
world. So, that's G3, there you have it.
Then you have the fourth largest economy
in the world, soon to be the third
largest economy, India, which is also a
major, at least a regional power, right?
It's one of the great powers in the
world, that's India.
Despite all of its problems, India is
still there, a major power. It's a it's
a growing power. I would not say a
rising power, I would say a growing
power. It's growing. India's going to
grow at 6 7% a year, hopefully. Maybe I
would like 10%, but let's see. So,
India's there. Then you have the
European Union, which is not really a
major player anymore. Europe is going to
be the backwater of the world in the
21st century, but still it's still a
player. So, it's like a G4 G5 situation
right now. And the US doesn't want that.
They would like a G2 situation. The US
doesn't want multipolarity, they want
bipolarity.
But it's too early to say that G2 is a
thing now, even though Trump would like
it that way.
Bhaskar Band says, "Land border between
China and Russia is pretty large." Well,
yes, pretty large indeed.
Then, what is so special about the
Ussuri River area that China chose to
occupy it, recognize it as their own in
current maps and in history?
Well, you see, you have to
if you want to understand this, I have
to tell you a story.
And and what does a story mean in in the
context of geopolitics? I will discuss
history here.
So, you see,
okay, let's look at the map. Obviously,
to understand what we are discussing
here, we have to see the map. So, let us
pull out
the map of the world. Where is it? Here
it is.
So, first of all, Russia and China, do
they have a border? Yes, sir. Yes,
ma'am. So, you see,
there's this border here.
This border, which is what? About 50 km
wide?
>> [laughter]
>> See here? Oh, it's not even 50 km. In a
straight line, it's about 39 km, but if
you if you
do the contours and all that, if you do
a contour integral, it may be about 50
km. So, on the one side, on the left, on
the west, you have the great nation of
Kazakhstan.
On the east, you have Mongolia. South,
you have Chinese-occupied
whatever. The East Turkistan.
And at the north, you have Russia.
50 km there.
Then you have Mongolia. You go further
east, and then you have the major
Russia-China border that is very very
significant, all right? Starting from
here, all the way
north of Manchuria
and all the way to the North Korea
border. So, south of Vladivostok, you
have a trijunction
of Russia, China,
and North Korea.
Okay? Russia, China,
Where is North Korea? Where is it?
Um I'm I'm I'm I'm
Yeah, so it's it's a trijunction.
Russia, China, North Korea. Let me zoom
in. This is indeed North Korea, isn't
it?
All right, North Korea. Yes. So, that is
the deal. So, it's a pretty long border.
Now, historically in the 19 what? 19
1969,
Russia and China nearly went to war.
The Ussuri River clashes, the Ussuri
River dispute. And there was this island
that Chinese called the Zhenbao Island
or whatever it is. It's somewhere here.
Which island is it? It will be a little
difficult for me to
to pinpoint the exact location of the
island.
Uh it will be somewhere in this area. Is
it this one?
Let me see if I can find it. Zhenbao.
Zhenbao Island. Zoom in. There we have
it. So, you can see now it's on the
Chinese side of the border.
But there was a time when the border ran
across the island, and this was disputed
by both nations. And the two nations
nearly went to war. The major military
clashes over here.
Hundreds of soldiers died. And the
Russians had decided to nuke China.
But the Americans came and rescued
China, and that's how things went. So,
now what's the deal?
Uh
what is special about the Ussuri River
region? And why does China seek this?
So, once again, we go to the map.
So, you see,
if you look at Russia's Far East, it is
enormous, as you can see.
But Russia
was based out of what?
Well, if you look at the origin of the
Rus' people,
their original capital, going back about
a thousand years, was Kiev.
It's now called Kyiv for some reason. It
was Kiev.
They were called the Kievan Rus'.
And later, the capital became Moscow,
Muscovy.
And for a couple of centuries, the the
Rus' were under the Mongol yoke
for a couple of centuries. And
eventually, the the Duchy of Duchy of
Muscovy became a big thing, and
eventually,
um Russia became an empire. And then
Russia started expanding eastwards,
eastwards, eastwards. And all these
territories, these were Tungusic peoples
who used to live here, Mongolic people.
I mean, north of Mongolia, you have a
big region which was historically also
Mongolia, which is now part of Russia.
So, the Russians, the Rus', they
expanded eastwards gradually. And what
did they seek? They sought fur, fur
trading in the frozen wastelands of
northern Eurasia. Nobody else wanted to
go there. So, the Rus' went there, and
they traded in furs, and they slowly
annexed all these territories. Now, the
Chinese claimed many of the territories
which are now currently part of Russia.
And the in the 1850s, the Chinese were
fighting major revolts.
The Dungan Revolt,
uh
uh and the the East Turkistan Revolt,
etc. The Hui Revolt.
So, they were fighting major major
revolts
in territories that they claimed as
their own in the west in the west of
what is today China. And you also had
the the gunboat diplomacy, the opium
wars that that was going on. The west
was bullying China, the Chinese century
of humiliation. So, during this time the
Russians took territory from China as
part of treaties that they signed with
the Chinese.
So, the the Russians, through legal
means,
took territory from the Chinese, major
territory, which is now part of the
Russian Far East. But the Chinese have
always historic has seen that as a
historical injustice. And they seek
those territories back. But the Chinese
say that the whole of Eurasia is ours.
Essentially.
So, that's the deal.
So, looks like the Ussuri River thing
was, you know,
one of the points of the dispute, but
the the Chinese claim way more territory
than what is on the map right now. So,
the Chinese claim Vladivostok, they they
claim they claim many other parts of the
Russian Far East, and it's going to be
an issue between Russia and China sooner
or later.
Right?
So, that's kind of the history if you
see that in the
in in the historical context, then
you'll understand that there's a lot
that's happened in this region. The
Chinese have claims, the Russians
actually have, you know,
facts on the ground.
The Chinese are revisionists.
They say that, you know, we had way more
territory and we want it back
eventually. That is the deal.
Aries Manticore says, "A small
suggestion. You can try to host live
stream on Kick as well." I'm live
streaming on Kick right now.
This live streaming that you may be
watching on YouTube, it is
also simultaneously being live streamed
to Kick, to Twitch, to X or Twitter.
It's being live streamed to LinkedIn.
And I sometimes live stream to Facebook
also at the same time. So, I'm live
streaming to multiple destinations at
the same time. Um yeah, so it's a good
suggestion, and I am grateful for you
that you have suggested this. I'm doing
that.
And many creators have been shadow
locked on YouTube. Kick is an
alternative with a much younger crowd.
Keep going. Thank you very much. Yes, I
know. I'm not I'm not sure about many
creators if this has happened to other
creators also on YouTube, but as you
know, my channel is
there's an upper limit that's been put
to my channel. It will not reach 950 for
the foreseeable future. Right? Somebody
in YouTube is not a big fan of me.
Probably some fine gentleman or fine
lady in YouTube India.
Somebody. Maybe I should do something
about it. We'll see about that. That's
okay. It doesn't matter.
Right, next.
Finding myself, Srishti Sap Kota says,
"As a local from Siliguri, I am seeing
rapid development, new industries,
bigger highways, more air activity.
Given the current geopolitical
situation, how will the state of
Siliguri be in the next 10 years?"
So, you're asking me to make a future
prediction. I don't really make future
predictions. I can, but let's let's
understand what we are discussing here.
We'll talk about Siliguri.
So,
excuse me. When we talk when we discuss
Siliguri, we're discussing this what is
called the Siliguri Corridor. So, there
is this city over here called Siliguri.
It's part of West Bengal. Even
Darjeeling is part of West Bengal.
And north of that, we have Sikkim,
obviously.
So, Siliguri is is part of West Bengal,
and to the east you have the great state
of Assam.
So, we have the Siliguri Corridor, which
is
roughly 30 km wide, 22 km, 23 km wide.
Well, well, well. Yeah.
Which connects the Indian Far East to
what they call the Indian mainland.
Right?
And the for some reason, our fantastic
leaders of the past, they decided that
we will accept this sort of map
with this so-called chicken's neck neck
that connects our Far East with the rest
of the nation.
So, in Siliguri, uh as Srishti says, she
is seeing rapid development, new
industries, bigger highways, better
highways, more air activity.
So, what So, I'm glad to hear that,
first of all, yeah. And obviously,
Siliguri is a very important uh
sectors you know, location for India.
It's very important that we have robust
infrastructure in the Siliguri region,
you know? Because see,
uh it is not it is obviously something
that borders the nation of Bangladesh.
And it is also not far from
Chinese-occupied Tibet. And it it also
borders with Nepal. So, it's an it's a
it's a region that is kind of
international if you want to consider
Bangladesh and Nepal international.
It is what it is, right?
And Bangladesh, obviously, is not was
historically East Pakistan. It has once
again transformed into kind of like East
Pakistan. It's not a very friendly
nation right now. It's a newly minted US
vassal state and kind of hostile towards
India.
So, there is that also.
So,
that's the current geopolitical
situation, right? That's the current
geopolitical situation. Even Nepal has
had a regime change very recently, a
so-called Janzee uh regime change,
revolution, whatever you want to call
it. And yeah, there is the question of
what kind of government is in Nepal
also.
So, given this situation, what will be
the state of Siliguri in the next 10
years? I would say that Siliguri should
be
in a better state in the next 10 years.
One of the One of the things I've heard
is that there's the there's a
significant infiltration of
Bangladeshis, illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators in the region. That's what
I've heard apocryphally. I'm not sure if
it is entirely correct. I've heard
there is a big
number of Bangladeshi infiltrators who
have settled in the region.
I am not sure if it's true. I hope it is
not true. But that is something that
with the government needs to do
something about. I would say urgently.
As
as in the case of the rest of the
country, the Bangladeshi infiltrators,
the illegals, need to be repatriated to
Bangladesh at the earliest. Um
So, hopefully, that is done
if the situation is indeed the case like
I said.
And I would say that,
you know, we need fortification of of
railways, highways, all of that in the
region. What else could happen in the
next 10 years? Well, the ideal situation
is that the Siliguri Corridor is
widened. And, you know, Rangpur, etc.,
returns to India.
That would be the ideal situation. If
the nation of East Pakistan, you know,
uh persists with its anti-India
stance, and if they give us an
opportunity, then if the opportunity
presents itself, we should uh take back
the Rangpur region,
Dinajpur, Rangpur, etc., and
uh you know, reintegrate it with the
motherland.
Uh so, that is something that could
potentially happen in the next 10 years.
Beyond that, uh it is
well, hard to say. Yeah, but oh, I'm
hopeful that uh the situation in
Siliguri improves even more compared to
what we are seeing right now.
King Ritwik says, "In the 1970s, India
was weak, India was poor. We needed the
help of the USSR \ Russia to
defend ourselves from the US and
Pakistan.
Still then, how could the USSR not
vassalize India? They saved us. Does
that make Mrs. Gandhi better than Mr.
Nehru?"
So, the question is,
was India
a vassal state of the USSR
in the 20th century?
India was definitely an ally
of the USSR.
India
proclaimed itself to be non-aligned.
And India did
do certain things that were not in line
with the USSR's interests. For example,
when the USSR invaded Afghanistan on
December 25, 1979, India opposed that.
Right?
But overall, India was aligned with the
USSR.
So, you could say that India and the
USSR were allies despite India's
posturing as
being you know, that it it was a
non-aligned nation. India was very much
on the side of the USSR.
And yeah, India was weak, India was poor
because of the economic model our
fantastic leaders had adopted,
Fabian socialism.
Yeah?
So, that was the case. And Pakistan was
in was in better shape than us. Um their
economy was doing better than than ours
until the the late 1980s, even the early
1990s, right?
And the Pakistanis had aligned with the
United States. They chose the winning
side. We chose the side that would
eventually lose the Cold War.
And we had to
rely on the USSR to
for support, especially in 1971. Right?
And so on. We know we know the
situation.
Now, did the USSR vassalize India?
Not quite. How do I say Why do I say
that India was not vassalized? Because
the USSR did not control India's foreign
policy. The USSR did not control India's
economic policy. When you vassalize a
nation, you control their economic and
foreign policies, and you leave them to
deal with their internal situation. That
you take care of, but you have to say do
what we say about your economic and
foreign policy and military policy. So,
that was not the case. That's why the
USSR did not vassalize India. Why did
the USSR not vassalize India? I would
say that they did they did not did not
see the need to do that.
There were other nations
that were aligned with the USSR in in a
variety of similar ways, and the USSR
did not seek to vassalize that. Was it a
good thing? Was it a bad thing? I think
it was something that was bad for the
USSR. If if they had adopted the
American policy of vassalizing other
nations
by
insisting that they control those
nations economic and
and and and foreign and military
policies like they did with Pakistan and
other nations, then the USSR would have
had way more power projection
capabilities. But for whatever reason
they chose not to do that and that's why
it was good for us, of course, yeah,
that we were not vassals.
Uh it is alleged that the USSR had
you could say allegedly bought out
certain politicians in India.
Allegedly.
Whoever they were.
But overall India was not a vassal. So
the USSR did not seek to vassalize
India. They sought to have India aligned
with them ideologically and
geopolitically, which we were.
So does that make Mrs. Gandhi better
than Mr. Nehru?
Look, overall Mrs. Gandhi was a far
better leader than than her father, Mr.
Nehru. There's no question about that.
No question about that. Overall
she was.
Aries Manticore says, "Should we focus
on
on creating multi-terrain AI drone
swarms in instead of jets and
submarines? Cheaper, faster, and more
potent with our missile technology." I
would say very much so, yes.
Right? But for that, we need
high-quality indigenous AI systems.
Does India have a single
homegrown
high-quality AI system?
Does India have
even one of those?
I haven't seen any. Maybe I'm wrong and
if if I'm wrong, then I'll be happy
about that.
But India, whether it is the private
sector or the public sector, whether
it's the government of India, whether
it's any IIT or whatever, or or some
private sector company,
does has anybody developed a
high-quality
AI model?
Similar to the quality that you have of
AI models that you have coming out of
the United States and China.
Do we have anything similar? We don't,
right? We don't. So to create these
drone swarms that that that are
AI-enabled, AI-equipped, you need
high-quality AI first of all.
Uh you can have some autonomy, etc.
That is not really See, for example,
during Operation Sindoor, we had these
ancient
anti-aircraft guns
that were not quite AI-equipped, but
they
they had been made kind of autonomous,
right?
They and they they were able to able to
take out all the Pakistani drones and
and whatever is whatever else the
Pakistanis lobbed at us.
So that's not quite AI, but it's kind of
it was kind of autonomous. It was these
were self-automatically targeting
weapons. So you take a 1950s weapon and
add some layers of software to it and it
becomes a tremendously potent thing. So
India is very good at doing these
things. Now imagine if India has its own
AI systems. Imagine what India will do
then.
So we should do that. I I 100% agree.
So you develop military AI systems
that can control swarms of drones. Let's
say you have a drone that costs
10,000 rupees. Get a thousand of those
like a drone of like a swarm of
mosquitoes and then you unleash them and
they all talk to each other, they know
exactly what the others are doing in
real time in space and time and they
connect with the satellite or whatever
it to the home base and the home base
you have AI and even on the drones you
have AI chips and then you can go and
unleash mayhem.
You can take out aircraft carriers with
that if you want to.
Right?
Just these flying drones. Now imagine if
you have
undersea drones or even
even surface, you know,
surface of the ocean drones.
So the Ukrainians had
they had attacked the Kerch bridge
bridge a couple of times. The bridge
that connects Crimea with the mainland
Russia.
They had one of the attacks was by was
was done with these autonomous boats
that were either remote controlled or
autonomously targeted, whatever it was
and it was able to damage the bridge.
So imagine you have small boats which
have explosives and they know what to
do, how to bypass defenses and whatnot.
Then imagine what those can do.
You can also have undersea vehicles,
robotic submarines, small ones
that may look like a large fish
or may or that may be the size of a
large fish, but that can unleash mayhem
because of its explosive
payloads.
And how do you control those? Well,
different technologies. So my point is
yes, we should do that.
We very much should do that.
Then eventually all of this will replace
jets and submarines.
Maybe not submarines, maybe not long
rangers. See, I'll tell you what's the
difference and where AI drone swarms and
these things
will not be able to do certain roles.
When you have fighter planes
some of the fighter planes have very
long ranges.
When you have strategic bombers, they
have ranges of thousands of kilometers.
Can a drone fly, let's say, 1,000
kilometers? Most likely not. Drones have
batteries, right? Lithium ion battery,
sodium ion, what whatever
technology of battery you use, but it's
going to have a limited charge, which
means it will have a limited range.
So you can't have you can only So drones
can only be used for tactical
uh
purposes, tactical warfare. You can't
use them for strategic purposes, which
is long-range stuff. So that's one of
the limitations of drones, but I'm sure
technology will eventually be able to
overcome those uh limitations as well.
But yes, India should focus on
indigenous AI, high-quality AI. India
should focus on quantum computing, very
important. And India should focus on
drone warfare and we kind of are, but
imagine we if we have our own AI system
and then we integrate that with our
drone swarms.
Imagine that. Yeah, we should do that
for sure.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "A pattern as to
how dictators who get funded from the
West to create havoc in their own
country or other countries later get
taken care of." Saddam Hussein, Pahlavi,
Zia-ul-Haq, Anwar Sadat, because they go
rogue or why? Okay.
So when we talk about Mohammad Reza
Pahlavi,
he was
uh
he was vassal, obviously. He was a US
asset
um who was ruling Persia.
And uh see,
so Pahlavi had ousted Mohammad
Mosaddegh.
Mohammad Mosaddegh had nationalized
Iran's oil industry. He had ejected the
British British Petroleum or British
Oil, whatever it was it was called
from Persia.
And that made the West very sad.
Very sad. It was such a heartbreaking
thing for the United States and for the
West, which is why Mohammad Mosaddegh
was ousted and Mohammad Reza Pahlavi
took over and he once again opened the
doors to the West and allowed the West
to siphon off Persia's oil.
So Pahlavi was eventually ousted in
1979.
He was not taken care of by the West. He
was taken care of by the by the by the
the
regime of the mullahs, the mullahs
by Khomeini.
Right? So
Pahlavi was not taken care of, you know,
he was not ousted
by the United States or the West. It was
an indigenous kind of thing, you could
say.
But when it comes to Saddam Hussein, he
was a US asset, wasn't he? The United
States used Saddam Hussein as a stick to
beat Iran with because Iran had ousted
their vassal, their puppet, Pahlavi.
So the US armed Saddam Hussein's Iraq
and induced Iraq and to go to war with
Iran.
That's the Iran-Iraq War of the 1980s,
a ruinous war that ruined both nations.
And eventually what was the outcome?
Nothing.
It was just ruinous and it it it ruined
both nations, especially Persia,
especially Iran.
So the United States used Saddam Hussein
for that specific purpose and then they
disposed of him.
They gave him the go-ahead to invade
Kuwait in 1990 1990 or whatever it was.
And then they said, "Why did you do
this? You are evil. We're going to smash
you now."
That's what they did to Saddam.
Zia-ul-Haq was funded by the US
um
in the aftermath of the Soviet invasion
of Afghanistan.
The Americans funded
um
the Pakistani IS, the Pakistani military
and uh
taught them how to use
what we now called terror now we call
terrorism,
the Mujahideen to fight the Soviets in
Afghanistan. And once that ended, the
Mujahideen were
rerouted into India into Kashmir. In the
1980s, the Pakistanis were
were
uh playing
havoc in Punjab, Indian Punjab also,
right?
So all of that was funded by the US. So
Saddam So Zia-ul-Haq was the Pakistani
dictator of the time. And then
Zia-ul-Haq goes he takes a he goes on a
airplane with the US ambassador
uh Arnold Raphel
and there's a crate of mangoes on the
plane and the crate of mangoes explodes.
Exploding a case of exploding mangoes.
Then Zia-ul-Haq dies. So the US decided
that it's enough of Zia-ul-Haq and we'll
have somebody else.
Most likely. And it looks like their own
ambassador was made collateral damage.
Anwar Sadat, different story. So the
question is, is there a pattern to this?
There is obviously a pattern to this. So
the US has historically been very fond
of dictators. They preach democracy and
human rights to the world, but if you
look at the number of regime changes
they've done in Africa and other
countries, you will see they always
install dictators in these countries
because dictators are easy to deal with.
Democracy is a messy thing.
You can't predict the outcome of what's
going to happen in the country in the
next 5 years.
An election can change everything and
you need to cultivate new assets. Why do
that? Invest in dictators. So, the US
preaches democracy to the world, but
they invest in dictators in various
nations across the world. They've done
so many regime change operations in
Africa in the 20th century,
in other parts of Asia,
so much more. So, there's a pattern and
eventually if a dictator becomes too big
for its for his boots, if he starts not
if he shows a tendency to now no longer
cooperate with the US
or be obstinate in certain demands,
you can always get rid of him, right?
And get have somebody else
uh
take over the country. So, there's a
pattern, no question about that.
If you look at Africa,
there are plenty of places where you
have dictators who
have been installed. Yeah.
And many of them and some of them are
going doing a really good job, actually.
Uh I shall not take names of countries.
Feel strong man says, "Your favorite
geopolitical joke joke apart from Stalin
Sri Lanka."
Favorite geopolitical joke? Well, that's
that's a googly like they say. Googly?
Is it a Is it a flipper? Flipper.
I can't think of a geopolitical joke
right now.
Let me think about it. If I can recall
something, I'll I'll let you know. I
can't think of a geopolitical joke right
now.
Shubham Vavere says, "Christopher
Columbus was Jewish. Searched for India
the day after the Spanish expelled Jews.
Is it true?"
Was the internal politics in the Maratha
Empire why we lost to Brits? We are
discussing sir, Shubham ji.
This if you look at the title of this
episode, it is geopolitics episode. We
are not discussing history today, sir.
If I start discussing history now, if I
start discussing science, then the
people who have come to
see me speak about geopolitics, they'll
be very disappointed. I have made a
promise in the title of the episode,
geopolitics.
I shall not break my promise, sir.
It is bad form to break your promises.
You have to keep your word if you are an
honorable person. So, I shall stick to
geopolitics today
and we can discuss history in a history
episode, all right?
Thank you, sir.
Hindutva rises says, "Do you foresee a
Pulwama type attack in the next month
considering the deep state's attack
attempt to dismantle the ruling party
have failed?"
I will not talk about next month. How
will I know?
See, understand this.
If you want to if you want me to say
whether something is will happen next
week or next month or
78 days from now,
then you are presupposing that I have
some very specific information.
Right? I can give you an answer to this
question only if I have very specific
information
that points in the direction. Now, I am
simply
a person who observes the world, who has
some understanding of how the world
operates and works. I have some
understanding of the patterns
and cycles of history which translate
into geopolitics. And that's the basis
on which I
speak about things. I don't have access
to classified information, to privileged
information.
I don't have access to information from
security agencies or intelligence
agencies.
And that's why I cannot answer a
question about whether I can
whether I foresee something happening
next month. What I can tell you
is that the likelihood of Pulwama type
Pulwama type attacks
in the next 6 to 12 months is higher
compared to
pre Pulwama or pre Pulwama.
Pulwama pre pre Pulwama.
See,
the Pakistanis See, understand this.
We have
Let's discuss three nations.
China,
India, Pakistan.
China
is about roughly four times more
powerful than India.
And India is let's see, I don't know,
what 10 times more powerful than
Pakistan? Maybe 15, maybe 20 times more
powerful than Pakistan.
So, there's a huge gulf between India
and Pakistan and also between
China and India.
So, when it comes to India and China,
knowing that China is four times more
powerful than us, we don't poke the
Chinese.
Right? We don't do things that will
irritate the Chinese, annoy the Chinese,
bleed the Chinese. We don't do a thing
like that.
But when it comes to Pakistan and India,
the Pakistanis despite being so much
less powerful than India, they keep on
poking, prodding, and trying to bleed
India. That's been their strategy from
day one, right?
From 1947 onwards.
That's always been the strategy. So,
they will continue that, but they will
seek to
continue continue this this strategy of
poking, prodding, and bleeding India and
conducting terrorist activities if
possible in India
while keeping it below a certain
threshold. What is a threshold? The
threshold that will that will lead to
war.
Because see, the
governments the Indian government's new
new policy, new doctrine, whatever you
want to call it, is that
a terrorist attack is going to be see
seen as an act of war.
But what kind of terrorist attack?
It's going to It's going to have to be a
major terrorist attack. So, how many
people died in the Pulwama attack? I
would I would say more than 20, right?
Something similar to that. So, maybe the
Pakistanis
will continue their horrific evil policy
of terrorism, but they'll keep it below
a certain threshold, perhaps.
Yeah. So, that could happen.
That there is a high possibility of that
uh continuing to happen. Maybe they will
instead of conducting cross-border
terrorism, maybe they will uh
maybe they will support various
individuals, let's say, who may be
Indian citizens. Like those alleged not
alleged They're not alleged doctors,
they're real doctors, right? Those
doctors who were recently apprehended.
They were all Indian citizens, right?
So, if they do terrorism in India, can
we blame Pakistan for that? Can't really
blame Pakistan for that. So, that's the
kind of things they will do.
Um
but yes, there is a higher
probability of this sort of thing
happening in the next 6 to 12 months. I
can't say about next month.
The reborn Xenophany says, "Do you see
Canada coming out of the job, housing,
rapidly increa- increasing inflation,
medical system, immigration crisis
anytime soon or that won't happen as
long as it keeps playing second fiddle
to the US?" Look,
Canada is destined to
play second fiddle to the US as long as
Canada exists.
Understand
that the United States
it
allows the existence of Canada.
Why does it allow the existence of
Canada? Because Canada is nothing but an
extension of the US.
It is a vassal state.
The US doesn't need to
occupy Canada or send the military to
Canada because Canada is harmless.
And Canada's
external policy, economic policy, it all
serves US interests.
Right?
And Canada doesn't have any leaders.
They have not allowed any real leaders
to emerge in Canada.
Do you see any leader who can take
Canada in a new direction?
Do you see any such person on the
horizon?
You only see mediocrities,
puppets,
puppets like Justin Trudeau.
Justin Justa
Justin Trudeau. What a loser of a
politician he is.
Absolutely zero leadership quality.
That's that person. Now you have this
gentleman called called Carney who has
been tasked with taking Canada in a
slightly different direction.
But to solve all the major problems, job
crisis, the housing crisis, inflation,
medical system, immigration.
See, immigration can be solved like
that.
Like that. Just change the policy and
enforce it.
Right?
But they won't do it.
And anyway, Canada is a nation of
immigrants if you
disregard the indigenous people who are
second-class citizens.
Right? Canada is a is a nation of
immigrants, but they want to keep
So, you can't really do that also. But
yeah, you can if you if
it's up to you.
So,
the situation in Canada,
it's in my opinion not going to change
significantly.
And Canada as long as it exists will
play second fiddle to the US. It simply
cannot break out of the US orbit. The
moment it goes against the US, the
moment it tries to decouple its
decision-making process from the US
interests,
there's going to be a tremendous
repercussion a set of repercussions for
whoever is the leader who has decided to
change course.
Won't happen. Canada is completely at
the service of the US and that's how it
is going to continue. So, I don't see
any major changes happening in Canada.
If there is an immigration crisis, well,
the roots of the immigration crisis
don't lie in Canada. They lie further
south.
And whatever else also. Yeah.
Essentially you have a bunch of
extremely mediocre politicians who are
doing a
terrible job.
And for some reason your people
Canadians keep
voting for them. So and I haven't even
discussed the Khalistan the support for
the Khalistani separatists who are
actually Canadian citizens, right? All
the all the nonsense. Uh.
Sankam Kumar says, is the US sniffing
war in the Indo-Pacific so ended a war?
The US
hasn't ended the the Ukraine war. They
seek to end it soon. They seek to Trump
wants a ceasefire now. I mean he's he's
been angling for a ceasefire from the
day he became president for the second
time.
But it's not really worked out for him.
But he is desperate to end the Ukraine
war. He wants a ceasefire.
Does he seek a ceasefire because they
want a war in the Indo-Pacific region?
Well, I would say there's a
high likelihood of war between India and
Pakistan in the next 2 3 years.
Um
much more major war than the last one.
The three-day war Operation Enduring
Freedom. It was a limited war, wasn't
it?
It wasn't a full-scale war because the
infantries
um you know the ground forces weren't
involved. It was all aerial warfare
mostly. Missile warfare, drone warfare.
Uh
mostly.
So it was not really a major major
full-scale war. But there is a high
likelihood of India and Pakistan going
to war in my opinion in the next 1 to 3
years. 1 2 3 years, right?
And uh war in Indo-Pacific. Now when you
say Indo-Pacific you obviously mean
something wider than India-Pakistan.
I don't foresee India and China going to
war right now.
In the near future at least.
But what about the Indo-Pacific region
like you say? Um
by that we
if we take India and Pakistan out of the
equation and India-China out of the war
equation, we're obviously discussing
the China-Korea-Taiwan-Japan
situation.
Right?
Is there a likelihood of war there?
I would say it would be stupid for China
to get embroiled in a war
over there.
It would be stupid for China to make a
move on Taiwan
at this point in time.
Wait another decade or two. Then take
Taiwan.
It is it is stupid to do it right now.
So I don't see a war happening
in in East Asia.
Unless something is done to provoke
China which China can't do anything
about which crosses certain Chinese red
lines.
For example, Japan going nuclear for
example. And I don't know. So you see
you see Japan is completely in the in
American control.
They are the Americans can make Japan do
whatever they want.
And they can also make Korea do whatever
they want. But Korea is not a military
power. Japan is.
So it all depends on the US. Do they
want to provoke China
into some kind of war in the
Asia-Pacific region?
Right?
Using proxies such as Japan and and
South Korea, maybe Taiwan.
If the Americans succeed in doing that
that could hurt
Russia uh sorry China to a certain
extent.
Um
But China will be obviously cautious
about this. So I think the there's a
high likelihood of war between India and
Pakistan in the next
couple of years or 3 years. Apart from
that I don't really see a major war
erupting anywhere else unless the
Americans do something magical
and induce China to go to war with Japan
or somebody.
There is Montecore says, could Russia
trigger a cold NATO conflict with Poland
and Sweden if the Ukraine conflict ends
a similar frozen conflict but with small
NATO countries? Would the US follow up
with the treaty in this scenario?
I would say it's not in Russia's
interest
to be in a perpetual state of war.
Right?
So when it comes to
nations like Poland and Sweden, these
nations are part of NATO.
And NATO has whatever clause in the the
treaty, right?
That an attack on one member of NATO is
an attack on all members of NATO. And if
one nation is attacked that's a member
of NATO, all other nations that are
members of NATO need to come to its
rescue and fight the aggressor.
So if Russia initiates a conflict with
Poland for example,
well that would be stupid because now
you're fighting directly with NATO.
And that won't end the way the Ukraine
conflict is going to end.
And
it makes no sense for Russia to do that.
Makes no sense.
Uh because now you're going to have the
full might of NATO directly against you.
The Ukraine conflict is a proxy
conflict.
It is Ukrainians dying for NATO.
But now Poland and see the the West is
is is a
the past years they've been transforming
Poland into a major military power.
Poland now is the most powerful
has the most powerful military in Europe
in Western Europe.
Even more powerful than Germany. There's
a reason why this has been done.
Let's take a look at the map, okay?
If you see the map, what do you have
west of Ukraine and Belarus?
You have Poland.
So Poland is the next frontier.
So the West is worried that if Russia
for whatever reason takes over Ukraine
and Belarus is already kind of you know
an ally of Russia,
then they could make a try to make a
move on Eastern Europe.
And all these nations used to be part of
the Warsaw Pact, Poland, Czech Republic,
Slovakia.
Um
Hungary and so on.
So that's why they are
they are
transforming Poland into a major
military power.
And it would be I would say not very
wise of Russia
to start a conflict with Poland. I mean
what do you get? What does Russia get
from a conflict with Poland? What's the
point of unending war?
A war a military conflict
makes sense
if it has clear
political and military objectives
that are
in line with your national interest.
Now is a war with Poland, Sweden,
whatever. Is it in line with Russia's
national interest? What are the military
objectives? What are the political
objectives? I'm not quite sure. So it
doesn't make sense.
Struggler says, what do you think about
Trump and Bill Clinton?
Donny and Bubba?
I don't think about those two in that
sense.
I Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> What can I say? Uh this is not the forum
to discuss that. I discuss these things
on Twitter.
>> [laughter]
>> Looks like it's looks like the rumors
are true.
Good god.
I don't know what sort of nation the
United States is really. I don't get
their culture.
Yikes.
James my dude my good friend James is
back.
China called over land at Tianzhu
meaning heavenly.
James uh what land are you from?
Are you Indian?
The Chinese called India heavenly.
Tianzhu means the center of heaven or
heavenly abode or whatever, right?
Yeah.
So the Chinese when referring to India
called it Tianzhu during the Tang
Dynasty era.
Heavenly. That is indeed true. Yeah.
But that's India, not the UK, not not
England. India.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh Nick Dreams says, the US is betting
big on AI. What will be the geopolitical
implications if
it turns out to be a bad bet or a bet
that takes a decade to pay off. We've
had similar things
decade big data climate change etc.
Climate change was a passing fad. It's
indeed a thing. Climate change is indeed
a reality, no question about that.
But there was a tremendous amount of
focus on climate change and now it's not
there.
Big data.
There was a lot of hype about big data.
Was that hype justified?
Of course it was justified. Now big data
is no longer a buzzword that is in
vogue.
But big data is the foundation of
artificial intelligence. Without big
data there is no AI.
The Yes, the US is betting big on AI.
Why is China betting so big on AI?
Can AI be a bad bet?
Absolutely not. AI is a transformative
technology.
A thousand years from today historians
will write about the pre-AI era and the
post-AI era.
And we see
for us what do we see? What do we What
kind of AI are we aware of? ChatGPT.
And what recently Gemini something has
come out.
And
there is an
Claude.
And there is the Chinese uh
uh whatever the names are, right? We
know ChatGPT is the most famous. So we
most people are aware of you know that
you can chat with ChatGPT, ask questions
and it tells you of stuff and yeah nice.
That's not
the only thing AI is.
There are different AIs
that you are not aware of.
There are military AIs.
What will a military AI do?
It's going to decide for you what is the
best strategy in a complicated
geopolitical situation.
Let's say or in a complicated war
situation, what is the best strategy to
use in real time that will outsmart your
enemy.
It can it can do game theory in real
time.
You see game theory is nice when you're
doing the prisoner's dilemma and
whatnot.
You can calculate those
situations easily, reasonably easily.
You can do a Nash Nash equilibrium and
whatnot. But when it comes to complex
situations with so many different
factors, you need a very high
intelligence to do the game theoretical
calculations.
And
you know, give you give you the dominant
strategies.
So AI can do that.
So AI is not going to be a bad bet bad
bet.
There's an AI arms race going on.
And whichever nation comes out on top is
going to rule the world for the next
1,000 years potentially.
How do we decide who has won?
The nation that achieves AGI and ASI
first is the is the winner. Once you
reach there, you will simply outpace
everybody else. And you will prevent the
others from catching up with you.
So AI is not going to be a bad bet.
And it's
it's not going to take a decade to pay
off. It's paying off right now, but
you're not aware of it. That's the
point.
You're not supposed to know these
things.
These things happen behind closed doors.
There are AI systems you can't imagine
that are currently in existence.
Okay.
General Dwayne says, "How in South Korea
the people are detached from culture?"
Look,
I have answered this question multiple
times and it's not a geopolitical
question, sir. Please, let's discuss
geopolitics today, all right?
I I took this question just a couple of
live streams ago in detail.
So you can check out maybe episode
either 306 or 304.
Biju says, "Do you think the Japanese or
German public deep inside know that
their country is a vassal state?" Some
of them are aware of it. Some of them
who are still able to think critically
will be aware of it.
Right?
Uh but most people in any nation
they just go with the flow.
See, what what do people want in life?
First of all, ask yourself this. What do
people want in life?
Firstly,
people are the same everywhere.
Now you will say, "What do I mean by
that?" Human beings are the same no
matter which country you go to.
Whether you go to African nations, Asian
nations, subcontinent of India, Europe,
East Europe, Western Europe, North
Africa, North America, South America,
wherever you go in the world, people are
the same. Now, what do I mean by that?
Everybody wants the same things.
They want a nice comfortable life. They
want a decent income.
They want decent living standards. They
want a good future for their children.
That's what everybody wants in every
country.
Okay?
Now, if you look at the state of
the conditions in Germany and Japan,
these are both first world nations.
These are the two nations that were the
major
you could say losers in the Second World
War.
Right?
Both were devastated. Then the Americans
helped these two nations rise back on
their feet, gave them first world status
and standards, allowed them to reach
those those those standards, allowed
those economies to become robust again,
right? But kept the nations enslaved.
Because they are worried about these
nations. So the situation is that
the ordinary people have good living
standards, way better than in India.
They have comfort. They have things that
you would call luxuries in India.
They have high incomes.
They have a
German Forget about Germany now, but
they had a you know, peaceful
law and order and whatnot.
Maybe not the case in Germany anymore
because the immigration thing, but
whatever.
The rule of law, all of those things.
So as long as you have all those things,
you will not complain too much, right?
And you have elections that happen
on a regular basis.
And then you have the education system
that tells you that, you know, your
country was evil and the Americans are
the beneficial benevolent
benevolent oppressors
benevolent friends of ours.
So you are in this nice cozy cocoon.
So most people will be happy
believing all that.
And you know, when somebody points out
you know,
facts that go contrary to what you
believe, it makes you very
uncomfortable. You you want to not think
too much.
You can just label put labels on those
people. You are conspiracy theorists,
blah blah blah, all that stuff.
So most people don't know about this.
Most people
don't care about this.
But there'll be some people who are
aware.
And recently somebody pointed out last
week to me that there was some Japanese
politician in parliament who said that
Japan is a colony of the US, a vassal of
the US. So I did happen to eventually
see that video clip and yeah, yeah.
That person was
an MP in Japan who was pointing out that
Japan is a colony of the US. And then
the Japanese Prime Minister's PA stands
up and she says that no, Japan is a
sovereign nation. Well, we all know
that's a convenient fiction, isn't it?
WBR says, "Do you know about the
Clinton-Lewinsky scandal?" You see, like
I said, I am not a news surfer.
>> [laughter]
>> That happened 20-30 years ago. How many
years?
Of course I know about it.
What's the point? How What does it have
to do with geopolitics?
Come on, man.
This is This was all over the
I mean,
everyone knows about that.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "Poland's
demographics have not been re-engineered
so much yet, unlike other parts of the
EU. Is it because they agreed to pump
their military-industrial complex
against the fake Russia is coming
threat?"
Potentially.
So there are two nations in
you could say Western you could say
US-controlled Europe
that have refused to
allow these immigrants into their into
their
nation. One is Poland, the other is
Hungary.
And both nations have to pay fines to
the
to the dictatorship in Brussels because
they don't want the immigrants. I think
the fines are like several million
dollars per day or something.
But they are willing to pay it.
Um
So why is this being tolerated? First of
all, if you pay the fine,
what can they do about it, right? It's
the price of freedom, I suppose.
And
and maybe there's some there's some kind
of tacit understanding that you know, we
don't change our demographics and we
allow you to
to
bulk up our military-industrial complex
and to turn Poland into a fortress
against Russia.
Maybe there could be that sort of
understanding, but obviously none of
that
is known in the public domain,
naturally.
Ankita G says, "Your opinion on the US
boycotting the G20 summit over alleged
persecution of whites in the in South
Africa.
Secondly, South Africa proceeding with
declaration without US nod. What do you
think a really bold step?"
Wow, okay. So like I said, I have not
really
um
I've not really um
studied what's happening in the G20
summit right now. I'll I'll do that in
my own sweet time in a week or so.
But okay, so the US has boycotted the
G20 summit. I remember Trump
a few months ago was putting out these
videos
on X and his social media. What is it?
Truth Social or something?
Of videos about whites being persecuted
in South Africa. There's a white
genocide happening allegedly in South
Africa. That's what he was claiming. And
Elon Musk was
was in agreement with Donald Trump.
So is that why the US has boycotted the
G20 summit? Has Has the US boycotted it?
Has I know that Trump hasn't gone,
but has Is there no US presence at all?
So I am not aware of this. The G20
summit is something that's happening
right now or it has it may just have
ended.
I I I don't surf the news. I don't try
to keep track of the latest information
in real time. I take my time to see
what's happening. So I'm not sure what
the deal is. But in case the US has
boycotted the G20 summit, like clearly
it has, okay?
Makes no difference.
The US will will The US will continue to
rule the world the way it does. And
whether it participates in the G20
summit or not makes no real difference
in the outcomes in in the world, right?
Trump is happy playing his game of
tariffs.
He is trying to achieve a certain
outcome in the Ukraine conflict. A
ceasefire.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh but his proposal is trying to
counterbalance China. He's trying to
encircle India and so on. All that is
going on. And G20 summit makes no
difference actually for him. So it's
okay. It's not important for him. Maybe
the G7 is more important for the US than
the G20.
So yeah,
if if that's the case, then
makes no difference to the US the
whether they participate or not. And
South Africa proceeding with a
declaration without US nod. What do you
you think a really bold step?
Um
Look, a declaration is a bunch of words,
right?
Who cares about declarations? I have
always emphasized the difference between
words and actions.
You may put out declarations of
whatever. At the end of the day, they
are symbolic.
It's words. Do you know how these things
are drafted? A bunch of
diplomats and bureaucrats come together
from various countries and then they
have intense negotiations all night
negotiations about what words to use in
which order to use them.
That goes on for multiple days.
And at the end of the day, there's a
great consensus. Yes, we have done it.
We have found the right order of words.
I have seen these G20 declarations.
Yeah.
It's a bunch of words.
Right? It has no real
massive
outcome on
on the shape of the world.
On the shape of history. It's okay. No
big deal.
So if the if the South Africans have
proceeded with a declaration without the
US nod, then it's not a really bold
step. The US also doesn't really care.
They won't really punish South Africa
for it. They will punish South Africa if
South Africa does some take some actions
that are counter to American interests.
Actions. Let's say that the South
Africans allow Russian mining companies
in South Africa. Now, that's something
that crosses red lines. Let's say that
South Africa allows certain Chinese
activities in South Africa that cross
perceived US red lines. That sort of
stuff will will invite retaliation. A
declaration, a bunch of words,
no one cares.
Kiran More says, "ISRO scientists are
are building Atomisus AI."
Oh?
Let's Let's find out. I thought in ISRO
you had engineers, right? ISRO is an
engineering organization.
Rocket engineers.
Let's see what this is. Is Isro
uh
uh Atomisus
AI. What is this?
Atomisus AI.
India's young innovators to launch
Next gen India origin intelligence
platform built with ISRO or something.
ISRO level engineering.
India blah blah blah blah blah Atomisus
Enough.
Indian origin uh
this is So, these engineers have
research exposure under ISRO. It's not
under ISRO. The The development of this
Atomisus AI is not under ISRO ISRO.
It's engineers who have exposure under
ISRO. Okay, that's different.
Affordable, powerful, sovereign AI
alternative, etc. empower
students, creators, families,
professionals, one unified ecosystem.
Okay, we'll see about that.
Too early to pass any judgment.
I'll have to see what this AI is.
What is it capable of?
You see,
AIs come in different flavors. Some
flavors are not for public consumption.
If this is another chatbot kind of
model, etc. I mean, it's a good it's a
good initiative, it's a good step, but
it you have to take it forward.
So, I'm I'm glad that people are taking
the initiative,
but it's not
ISRO scientists who are doing it, first
of all.
It is some a bunch of people who have
had exposure to ISRO in the past
who are building it. And
that's great. That's great.
But, you can't build
an AI that is a competitor
to ChatGPT or or or Claude or
Gemini or the Chinese systems
with small money. You need really large
num
amounts of money to do that. So,
that's what India needs.
India needs to invest billions of
dollars worth of money into AI.
Um
A number of a bunch of entrepreneurs
doing it is a great step, but I hope
that if they do a good job of it, they
should get more funding to create a
proper
competitor to the American and Chinese
systems. Okay, Teja Reddy says, "Can you
explain about the Gaddafi case in ICC?"
I don't remember what it was. That was
in the '80s, was it?
The Lockerbie bombing?
I suppose that was it. There was this
Was it the Pan Am aircraft
that was blown up over Lockerbie in
Ireland? Was it Pan Am? It was blue
because I've seen the wreckage when I
was a kid.
In the media, obviously. I didn't go
there.
Um
>> [snorts]
>> Let's see.
Lockerbie
bombing.
Was it Pan Am? Pan Am 103, right?
Yeah, my memory serves me right. It was
a blue thing. Pan American Airlines no
longer exists.
And did this eventually lead to a case
against Gaddafi in the International
Criminal Court?
Possibly.
And then
and then some
Libyan citizens were sanctioned or
jailed or whatever. I don't remember the
details, but yeah, something like that.
It's been a long time, wasn't it?
Uh Phantom says, "I see a lot of players
in the Indian Ocean. What can happen if
Indian influence on the Indian Ocean
slips off?" It It'll be bad for India.
You see,
if you have
an erosion of Indian Indian influence in
the Indian Ocean, then you'll have other
players who become dominant dominant
actors in the Indian Ocean region.
Let's take a look at the map quickly.
>> [clears throat]
>> What is the Indian Ocean region, first
of all?
So,
the Indian Ocean region is
the Indian subcontinent.
It is
the west coast of the sea of Saurashtra
or the so-called Arabian Sea.
And then you have the East Africa coast.
You have Madagascar, you have Mauritius
and Réunion.
Then you have
Perth in Australia where cricket matches
last only 2 days, apparently. And then
you have uh
Indonesia,
right? Sumatra. And then you have the
Andaman Sea and the Great
Kalinga Mahasagar. That's the Indian
Ocean region.
But, the area of our interest is, you
know, the western and eastern Indian
Ocean, which is the so-called Arabian
Sea and the the so-called Bay of Bengal.
So, if India's influence
you know, there's an erosion of that
over here, then you'll have other
players becoming major actors over here.
Let's say the Chinese navy becomes a
major player here. They can
make life difficult for India.
We have See,
we have all kinds of shipments
coming in maritime shipments coming in
to various ports in India. We have a
port in Gujarat, Mundra, is it?
It is a major port in Gujarat, Mundra.
We also have uh
port in Mumbai,
Navasheva. We have other ports. We have
a major port transshipment port coming
up in the Andamans.
And all of that, if the Chinese become
the dominant maritime player here, they
can choke off our
our shipments.
And that becomes a problem for us. Let's
say that the Pakistanis suddenly in the
next 5 years have more and better
submarines than India. And once again,
it's a major problem for India. And they
can create havoc with our shipping lanes
and whatnot.
So, you can see it's it's a it's a
disaster for India. India has to control
this region.
Which is why we need more ships. We need
better ships. We need a diversity of
ships. We need distributed lethality of,
you know,
not just one kind of ship. You don't You
don't want concentrated lethality. You
want your lethality to be distributed
over a wide area of the ocean. What is
lethality?
To make a long story short, lethality
means missiles, naval missiles.
Yep.
Naval firepower.
So, yeah, we need to ensure that our
influence does not decline in the Indian
Ocean region. We need to augment our
influence and our control of the region.
Minimalist Maverick says, "What's going
to happen to Antarctica? What's in the
mind of Russia, China, US, India
annexing regarding this? I want it to be
Indian territory and I want my own house
there." Well, you know what? I would
love to have a house.
One of my holiday homes in Antarctica. I
can go there for half an hour every
year.
>> [laughter]
>> It's frighteningly cold. What's going to
happen to Antarctica?
See, everybody wants a piece of
Antarctica.
And various nations have claims
on Antarctica. Would you like to see the
claims? Let's Let's take a look at that,
okay?
Argentina has a claim. Chile has a
claim. Let's take a look at
claims territorial claims on Antarctica.
Let's see.
The The English have a claim. Would you
believe it?
I suppose some of the French would have
claims.
Argentina, Australia. Australia has a
claim. Yes. Chile, France, New New
Zealand has a claim on Antarctica.
Norway, who the hell are the Norwegians
to claim Antarctic territory?
So, here we have various claims, which
most of them are jokes. I mean, the UK
claiming Antarctica is a joke, isn't it?
Absolute laughable, risible joke. UK,
Norway, who does Who do the Norwegians
think they are claiming Antarctica?
Australia, I can understand that.
France, well, they have territories,
you know, in the southern Indian Ocean.
New Zealand, well, we could understand
they can at least make a nominal claim.
Argentina,
UK once again,
Chile also, right?
So, that is the deal.
Now, you see, most of these nations are
in no
condition, they're in no position
to actually act on these claims. These
are all nominal claims,
just for namesake.
To To play the game, you know, to
pretend to be a big power. The UK
claiming Antarctic territory, what kind
of a joke is that?
And Norway,
>> [laughter]
>> New Zealand.
I mean, no disrespect to these nations,
but it it is not
It's not going to work out for them,
right? If they try to
actually
act on those claims. So, what's going to
happen to Antarctica?
See, there are certain nations, several
nations that have bases in Antarctica.
These bases are typically
observatories, research stations,
scientific research stations. The
Americans have plenty of this.
The Chinese have it.
India also has at least a couple of
Antarctic stations that are typically
manned around the year, if I'm not
mistaken. Hopefully around the year.
I'd be disappointed if it's only 6
months a year or whatever. We'll see.
The Chinese have that. Russians The
Russians have it.
So, the nations that actually maintain
bases on Antarctica, those have to be
taken more seriously.
Let's take a look at which nations have
Antarctic bases, right? Let's see.
List
list of nation Come on, my spelling. of
nations with Antarc
Antarc tic
bases.
Let's see how many we have.
New Zealand, okay. Australia, Chile
France, Norway, Argentina
Chile again, Germany, nice. Japan,
Nippon, good good to have you.
Um Ross Okay, let's see. That's
nonsense. Research stations in
Antarctica. How many Do we have a list?
Do we have a list? Okay, US 25%
Argentina, Chile, UK, France, Australia,
Russia, Japan, China, Italy South
Africa. India has only 1.89%.
So, India is has a presence there. It's
always India is all about slogans and
symbolism. We have a couple of stations.
Yes, but
we don't take it seriously. That's how
India does everything.
Thus far.
I would like to like to like that to
change. So, that's the situation. If
there is
I think there's a treaty that says that
Antarctica has to remain
neutral territory.
And no nation can actually
seek to occupy it.
And these treaties well, they will
continue to do exist as long as the
current world order exists. If there is
a major upheaval in the world order,
well, some nations may make a move on
Antarc those who those that can.
So, what's going to happen? We'll see
about that. Thus far, it is neutral
territory.
Abhinav Kulkarni says, "Abhijit Avneet
detailed geopolitics podcast." Well,
okay, thank you for the suggestion. I'm
not really doing podcast that much
anymore.
Very rarely, very infrequently.
So, we'll see. But anyway, thank you for
the suggestion, sir.
Dhruv Bhatnagar, well, thank you very
much. Thank you.
WBR says, "Is MN
Is Mongolia a safeguard for Russia
against China? Groups like the Buryats,
Yakuts, Tuvans, etc. are getting
militarized due to war." Which war?
Is it a war?
Where is it?
Ukraine war?
So, is it a problem for China if it
decided to go in? You see, yeah, this is
a good question. We'll go to the map.
>> [clears throat]
>> Ask yourself a question.
Okay, very pragmatic geopolitical
question. Why does Mongolia still exist?
You see, there's a story, right? When
Stalin was shown a map of India
when Joseph Stalin was shown a map of
the Indian subcontinent, he asked, "What
is this little island to the south of
India?" And the Indian ambassador said,
"Sir, you see, this is Sri Lanka. It is
a separate nation." And Stalin said,
"Why is it a separate nation?
If you are a great power, why don't you
take it? Why is it a separate nation?
Why is it independent?" And the Indian
ambassador had no no answer to that.
So, why is Mongolia, which is sandwiched
between massive Russia and massive
China, why is it independent?
It is independent
because it's a buffer state.
It was once the greatest empire in human
history.
Today, it is unfortunately and sadly
a nation that's almost powerless.
Doesn't have a great military.
And you see, it's not geopolitically
relevant except as a buffer state
between Russia and China.
About half of Mongolia is occupied by
China. The Chinese call it Southern
Mongolia, and it's under China's
occupation.
And there is a part of Mongolia that's
north of present-day Mongolia that has
been incorporated into Russian
territory.
So, historically, Mongolia was much
larger. Now, it's been taken bites have
been taken out of it, and whatever is
left is a buffer state. It's still
massive.
So, so why does it exist in the shape
and form that it does? Because the
Chinese and the Russians need something
between them. If they have a much longer
there is a much higher likelihood of
Russia and China going to war.
So, it's better to have a buffer state
between them. A a nation that can't
threaten anybody, and you allow it to
exist. And I can go into the history of
Mongolia and what happened during the
Soviet era, etc., but that's maybe for a
different day.
Yuvraj Gupta says, "Jan 25, you said
raising standard session."
Did I?
Should we have
a live stream about how to raise your
standards?
I suppose we could do that.
Yeah, I did kind of say something like
that. So, what I did was I did all those
live streams, right? I did 50
work with me, study with me live
streams. That was raising your
standards. What was the
purpose of those 50 live streams I did?
I'll I'll show you once again.
So
the past 2 3 months, I've stopped that
now, but the past 2 3 months, I did
those live streams, which are no longer
visible
uh 1 second. I had opened this for a
second. Latest, let's see. Are those
live streams visible anymore? I think I
have unlisted those, but you will find
those live streams
over here.
If I open up the playlists, 1 second.
So, I'm not sure. It will be somewhere
there. The point is why did I have those
those live streams?
That was
how to raise your standards. See, if you
want to achieve something big, you have
to spend a lot of time working on it.
Right? And that was the purpose of those
live streams. So, that that was kind of
what I did.
You know, 8-hour 8-hour 8-hour sessions
of me writing.
So
the objective was to demonstrate
that
to achieve something to to create
something, you have to spend a lot of
time and effort doing that. So, that was
kind of along the lines of raising your
standards. But I could perhaps do a live
stream specifically dedicated to how to
raise your standards. We'll we'll see
about that.
The Krish is a new member. Well,
welcome, sir. Let's us let us welcome
the Krish to
the the channel's membership. Thank you
very much for becoming a member. I
really appreciate that.
Okay. Biju says, Biju Saikia says, "What
do you think about the BRI project? How
is it going, and when will it be
successful and will it be successful?"
The BI BRI project has been on for a
very long time, hasn't it?
The Belt and Road
uh the Belt and Road initiative of
China. What was the objective of the BRI
project? The objective of the BRI
project was to create a massive amount
of infrastructure in Eurasia that would
connect China
um with
the rest of the Eurasian nations.
And uh
it would allow China to export its goods
to all the Eurasian nations.
And uh that that sort of thing. So, if
you control
the infrastructure of industry, if you
control the infrastructure of commerce
then you control much of the economy of
the region.
Right? And you have and you get ready
access to all kinds of resources, maybe
raw materials and all that.
So, that was that is the purpose of the
BRI project. It's to increase Chinese
influence and power across Eurasia. They
have a complementary project called the
Maritime Silk Road, which seeks to
create maritime trade routes and
shipping lanes between China and various
nations, including African nations, to
extract
uh natural resources from those nations.
And obviously, all the objective of all
of this is to increase China's power.
Now, what do I think about it? It's a
great initiative.
It it shows that China is an ambitious
nation. It's a nation with specific very
very clear vision for the future.
It shows China has great leadership. But
how has this gone thus far? It's not
worked out very well for China.
Many nations have stopped participating
in the BRI.
And if you look at the the
the Pakistan portion of the BRI, the
China-Pakistan Economic Corridor, it's
it's
not really worked out at all, right?
It's not paid off the way the Chinese
wanted it to pay off, and so and so on.
So, it's it's not gone very well for
China. That's the problem that the
Chinese have faced
thus far.
Uh Krish Krish I EXC says, "How can soft
power of a nation affect geopolitics?"
Um
so, this is not a criticism of you,
Krish I EXC, but
what I have consistently observed is
that Indians are obsessed with soft
power.
Soft power, soft power. Okay, I'm not
trying to criticize you. I'm just
putting forth an observation of not you
specifically. It's a pattern that you
see across all Indians or all the or
most Indians.
That we are obsessed with soft power.
I'll tell you
what is the relevance of soft power in
geopolitics.
Minimal.
Soft power is
useless
without hard power. If you don't have
hard power, but you have soft power
it gives you nothing whatsoever in
geopolitics.
But you if you have hard power
then soft power can
sometimes augment it.
Sometimes you can get things done
through soft power if you have hard
power.
So, if I have a big stick
but I talk to you nicely sir let's sit
together.
Let's work it out. I need these things
from you. Would you be so kind as to
give it to me? Then maybe you will give
it to me.
So, I'm not using hard power here to
convince you or to bully you. I'm
talking to you nicely, and I'm
convincing you through my good behavior.
That is soft power. But if I did not
have that stick
behind my back or at my disposal, then
you would not listen to me, right? So,
that's how it works. Soft power is
useless and pointless without hard power
to back it up.
Uh right angle says, "Please tell other
delusions of people of Bharat live."
Well, we can discuss that in a different
live stream. Today we're going to
discuss geopolitics, not delusions of
people of Bharat, which are
there are plenty of, of course.
Uh so, yeah, even yesterday somebody had
asked me reminded me about that. So,
maybe I can perhaps do
yeah.
So, maybe I will clip I will take a
screenshot of of this comment.
And maybe in a future live stream I can
discuss a few more delusions of the
people of Bharat, sure.
Om Sushant Bharadwaj says, "A life is
measured in what we give,
not take. Let time flow through you to
others." Well, okay, that's not a
question, but it's a statement, and I
agree with you.
Well, it's up to you. You know, you can
measure your life in whichever way you
want, but I think this is a good way of
measuring life.
What
What is the purpose of life is what many
people ask, right?
What's the purpose of life? So, you can
decide what you what the purpose of your
life is, but for me
I would say my life has been a good life
if I am able to contribute more to
society than I take from society.
I think that would be a good a life well
lived. So, yeah, I that kind of echoes
what you're saying here. So, yes, I
agree with you.
Karan Well, Karan has no question, but
thank you so so much, Karan. Really
appreciate it. Thank you, sir.
Animesh Paul says, "Today is my
birthday." Well, first of all, Animesh,
happy birthday to you. And wish you many
many happy returns of this fantastic
day for you.
Uh I'm a tech worker doing well in life.
I'm deeply grateful for what I what I
have,
knowing not everyone has this privilege.
How can I become a better person with
higher standards?
Okay, so this is not geopolitics, but
since it's your since it's your
birthday, I'll answer in brief. How can
you become a better person with higher
standards?
Don't compromise.
Don't lie to yourself.
All of us in some way or the other we
kind of lie to ourselves, right? We make
some promises to ourselves, and then and
then we break those promises.
And what is a compromise? It's breaking
the promises you make to yourself. You
know what you're capable of what what
you're capable of.
You know what you want to achieve in
life. Maybe you have some dreams, some
hopes, some aspirations.
And if you compromise on those things by
settling for
an easier life, or maybe settling
because of whatever reasons,
then you're compromising and that you're
lowering your standards. So, you have to
be uncompromising.
It's very very hard. It's easy It's very
easy to say these things. It's very hard
to do that in real life.
But only the hard things make you
better, right?
So, you And And sometimes you have to
compromise certain There are certain
times when you don't have the resources
at your disposal to achieve what you
want to achieve. So, maybe you delay
what you want to achieve, but you don't
postpone it forever, right? So, that's
the kind of thing it is. I mean, I can
go on about this in detail, but the main
thing is don't lie to yourself. Whatever
promises you make to yourself, you you
keep those promises to yourself.
Otherwise, you will lose your own
self-respect.
And don't compromise
with whatever your core goals and
objectives are. Don't please don't
become people pleaser. That is also one
sign of lowering standards.
Okay, so these are some of the things.
All the best, Animesh, and once again,
happy birthday to you.
Bhuvan says, "Why no government action
on anti-Indian online racism?"
Well, the government of India
can only act
within
the geographical confines of India.
India's sovereignty is within its
geographical confines, right? Now, when
there is
some activity coming from outside of
India,
what can India do about it?
Can the government of India take action
against people
legally? Can the government of India
legally take action against somebody who
is in a different country?
What can we do?
We could perhaps request the government
of that country to do something. But if
it's a democratic country, then the
government of that country will say that
these are people
who are exercising their rights as per
the law of our country. In in our
country we have freedom of speech.
So, they will say what what they want to
say. We can't we can't do anything about
it. We are friends of yours, but we
can't control all our people. Then what
do you do about it?
The real reason
this is a problem for us is is because
we don't control the platforms on which
there is anti-India online racism, all
these social media platforms.
We don't control them. We don't own
them. We didn't build them because we've
been sitting doing something else.
We have never bothered to build our own
platforms that are as good or even
better than what the West has built.
We don't have that ambition, right?
That's the problem. So,
what can the government do about it?
Well, the government See, you can't ask
the government to build a Twitter
or a Facebook.
Private entrepreneurs have to do that.
And there are people with these ideas,
but they who will fund them?
It's high risk, right? India, we don't
want risk.
We don't want risk. We don't like risk
over here. There is there is a very low
appetite for risk in India. Very low
risk tolerance threshold we have. We
want guaranteed our returns.
So, that's why you See See, if you go to
Silicon Valley, there's a very high
appetite for risk.
Um
Angel investors they typically spread
their bets
on, let's say,
20 companies. And even if two of those
bets turn out to be good, they're going
to make their money back. But that
mindset doesn't exist in India. We have
venture capital in India and all, but
their mindset is different. So, that's
where we are.
Any solutions as Karan to pollution
problem in India?
Well, that's a long big topic. I can't
answer that in detail.
Um
What's the solution? One solution is we
go full on
full in all in on nuclear power.
See, right now a lot of the electricity
we generate is through uh coal
based power plants. We we have to burn
coal for that, right?
And if you could move to nuclear,
then that that could you know, reduce
all the pollution. And there are so many
other things. We could move to electric
vehicles then.
Because see, if you move to electric
vehicles completely, but your
electricity electricity still comes from
fossil fuels, then it's not going to end
the pollution.
So, there is that. There are many other
factors which we can take care of which
we can
think of.
N K says, "Who is more powerful, Prime
Minister or Supreme Court of India?"
This is not a geopolitical question,
sir. This is a question about the
internal matters of India, which I don't
discuss.
See, I can't fight every battle. I can't
talk about everything. I speak about
three very broad topics, geopolitics,
history, and science.
I will not discuss Indian politics. I
will not discuss these internal matters
of India. That is not my my battlefield.
So, no comments.
No comments. Sorry.
Uh D R C, thank you, sir or ma'am. Uh
the question is is
Anglo
>> [laughter]
>> Uh is the Anglo-Saxon empire trying to
alter Indian history, anthropology, and
epistemology using state-sanctioned
racism? What about never do an enemy a
small injury by Machiavelli?
Um
Is the Anglo-Saxon empire trying to
alter See, what they're trying to do
what they're not trying to do it. They
have been doing it for the past couple
of centuries.
They have
set the narrative about India, about
India's past, about India's society,
about India's culture.
They have
fooled you all
and the world that there is a very evil
caste system in India.
Four
four castes.
They instituted those castes.
Right?
They made it part of the Indian legal
system,
the Indian government system. And after
1947 we So, the point is they have
written our history for us, and we teach
that
to our students. They have set the
narrative about everything that is to do
with India, about India's history, about
India's culture Like I said, everything.
And now we also have racism that's
coming out from various places. Now, one
interesting thing that's happened in the
past couple of days on X or Twitter
is that every account now
it shows the country of origin.
So, you'll see a lot of these anti-India
accounts,
if you look at the country of origin, it
it will show South Asia. So, you can
choose to show your country or your
geographical region. And obviously,
since Twitter is an American company, so
they will show this they will say South
Asia, not Indian subcontinent. So, when
an account you find it to be South Asia
based,
and it is spewing hate against Indians,
it is guaranteed to be either Pakistanis
or Bangladeshis.
Could be some other countries, but
mainly Pakistanis and Bangladeshis.
So, there are a lot of accounts like
these. And those obviously are in line
with
you could say
the Anglo-Saxon agenda. Right?
And And you have all these bots bot
farms and what that that have been
amplifying that have been creating and
amplifying narratives against India in
the past since the year 2022, mostly.
Even before that it was there, but now
it's coordinated.
Um so, they are not trying to alter
Indian history. They have set the
narrative of Indian history. They have
set the set the standards of Indian
history. They have decided which dates
what happened. They have decided which
what was the date of the birth of the
Buddha, which day which year Kanishka
ruled, which years Kanishka ruled?
The Mauryan Empire, we don't even know
if those dates are correct.
There were multiple Chandraguptas in
Indian history.
When Megasthenes writes that I was at
the court of Sandrakottos in Palibothra,
he's talking about a king called
Chandragupta in Pataliputra.
But which Chandragupta? There have been
multiple Chandraguptas in our history.
So what if the Mauryan Chandragupta
Maurya was way before?
Before Alexander.
Yeah?
That would place the date of Chanakya
also several centuries before. It would
change the date of the birth of Gautam
Buddha.
So all of this has been decided by the
West and we simply slavishly, blindly
follow that.
A lot of this needs to be looked into.
And yeah, so by controlling what the
what you think of your history, they
control your minds and that way that's
how that's how they can control the
entire country.
The entire culture.
Very powerful.
Rohan Suneja says, "How Scandinavia
became so rich historically poor?"
How did Scandinavia become so rich?
Historically it was poor.
Mhm, interesting question.
How did Scandinavia become so rich? I am
I'm not sure I can answer the question
right now. I can't think of the
historical context in great detail. I
will have to give you the answer to this
question. Interesting question, but I
haven't really studied the historical um
the flow of history.
Scandinavia
very interesting region, but interesting
only in recent times. Historically, like
you yeah, you're right. It was not
really very prosperous.
Yeah, I'm not sure I can answer this
question right now, but interesting
question. Maybe in the future I can take
it up.
Krishna Krish EX says, "Who really won
the Cold War?"
The United States won the Cold War.
The United States.
James says, "European people built all
positive aspects of the modern world due
to their intelligence, culture, and the
bravery. Our knowledge is far more
superior. I'm tired of I'm tired of
pretending. You have lived there, all
right?"
Yes, my dear friend James, I have indeed
lived in the West on several occasions.
Uh European people, fantastic people, no
question.
Fantastic intelligence, culture,
bravery, uh knowledge,
very superior.
I'll tell you what. What the Europeans
did was they
excelled,
they outperformed the rest of the world
in the systematic application of
organized violence.
Okay?
That's what the Westerners did.
And who excelled among the Westerners?
It was the English
who excelled at the organized and
systematic application of
large-scale organized violence.
They they excelled. They mastered this.
The the the English are a race of
merchants who have guns.
And their objective is to extract the
maximum profits out of any endeavor.
That's what the English are.
And in the past 500 days they they
destroyed the world, plundered the
world, and amassed all the wealth they
could,
and kept the world and
impoverished the world, the rest of the
world, and keep it kept it impoverished,
and then constructed this this
global rules-based world order in which
they set the rules, the others follow
the rules, and then they set the
narratives,
and then they wrote the history of the
world.
That's how you claim that you are that
the West is superior.
You see, let let's look at this from a
different perspective, a perspective
that's different from from anything I've
said before.
Okay, hear me
let me put out a completely different
perspective from anything I have said
before.
This is the age
of Kali.
This is the Kali Yuga.
If you win in Kali Yuga, it doesn't mean
you're better. It means you're evil.
Right?
So victory in Kali Yuga means you are on
the side of the evil forces.
And that's what's happened, but we're
going to retake the world
sooner or later.
Anyway, James, I do appreciate you very
much. I do.
Uh B 2 Psyche says, "Uh are we going
through the fourth industrial
revolution? How How long will it last?
How can we take advantage of it?" Okay,
industrial which industrial revolution
is this?
Um
you had the industrial revolution in the
what? 17th, 18th centuries?
Um
then you had I don't know which
industrial revolution this is. Um
I'm a little muddy on the history on the
on the in the chronology of which was
which.
Okay, but we are going through a massive
transformation. It's a transformative
period of um
of human history because of the
technology that have emerged, right?
Artificial intelligence. How long will
it last? How can we take advantage of
it?
This could last a thousand years.
AI could transform the world and whoever
wins the AI race, the AI race for AGI
and ASI could rule the world for a
thousand years if they don't get it
wrong catastrophically.
So
yeah, the next next couple of decades
are going to be transformative. We're
going to have the rise of very, very
powerful AI systems.
And we also seen transformative leaps,
quantum leaps in robotics technology.
So you marry the two,
artificial general intelligence or or
super intelligence with high
with cutting-edge robotics, you're going
to have a Terminator-like situation.
And whoever is able to merge these two
technologies, either the US or China,
India is not a player so sadly right
now. Right now, I hope it changes, but
India is not a player right now. So
whoever wins this race is going to rule
the world for a very long time.
Uh how long could it last?
Like I said, it could last a thousand
years. At least a century or two
minimum.
It's going to be the start of a new
imperial era. Whoever wins this race,
it's going to start a new imperial era,
a new imperial cycle. An imperial cycle
is roughly two and a half centuries.
That's That's what history That's what
history tells us.
So how can we take advantage of it?
By participating in the goddamn race.
India needs to participate. Is India a
player in robotics right now? No, no,
no, no. Is India a player in AI right
now? No, no, sir, not at all, sir.
What the
hell are we doing?
How can we take advantage of it? By
participating, by becoming a major
player.
We are not a
Okay, anyway.
UVX says, "Hungary minister says we will
pay no tax for illegals." Thoughts?
Yeah, that's been their policy for a
very long time, for years.
I would say kudos for having a spine.
Yeah?
Gulliver says, "Did you just 1984-ize
Germany and Poland? I guess you're
right, Orwellian in spirit, at least
spineless or not. But I hope that they
don't sell that commodity which Faust
did."
Did I 1984-ize Germany and Poland? Big
Brother
Orwell, right?
Uh Orwellian in spirit. Um
Well, Orwell
Orwell was kind of a visionary, wasn't
he?
He kind of saw the direction in which
the world could go and it it's kind of
gone like that.
If you look at the European Union, you
have a Big Brother sitting in Brussels
who controls what happens, who decides
what happens, and the people
don't have the agency to change that
anymore.
If you are a citizen of of Italy, if
you're a citizen of Germany,
if you're a citizen in in in
non-occupied Ireland,
and you don't want certain things in
your country, you are powerless to to do
anything about it. You don't have the
agency.
All you can do is obey, otherwise you're
going to face consequences. So yeah,
that's that's what's happening. Germany,
Poland, not so much. Poland at least has
control over immigration. It's not
allowing any weird immigrants into into
its
across its borders, which is a good
thing.
So
yeah, that's the situation in Germany.
Yeah. What is that commodity that Faust
uh sold? I can't quite recall. Let's
let's
let's Faust Faust. Yeah.
Faust, of course, Faust was uh
What is the commodity that he sold? I
can't remember right now.
It's been a while.
Okay, selling your
>> [laughter]
>> selling your soul to El Diablo. Maybe
that. Okay, Deva says, "Namaste. Will
debasement trade accelerate in 2026?"
I I don't know. I'm really sorry.
Can't say. I
I'm not keeping track of any of this.
Sorry.
Um
Amisha says, "When will the black hole
and Maya chapter come next?" Long time.
Yeah. It's been a while, isn't it? See,
the mirror mirrors of Maya series, it's
it's not easy to write.
You have to come up with a new story,
completely fresh story each time.
It's not something that I can write one
chapter a week. It's a new story each
time. It's a new short story each time.
I need a completely different character,
and I have to
think about a really interesting story.
So that's difficult. It will not come
Sometimes you may have a couple of
releases in a month, maybe sometimes
once in 3 months, I can't say for sure.
Black Holes
I'm wondering what to do with the Black
Hole series right now. Obviously, I'm
I'm continuing it. I'm working on that.
But, should I continue to release each
chapter
as a standalone ebook or should I now
that I've released three, I think three,
right?
Should I then now just complete the book
and release it at one go? I I have to
think about that.
So,
I'm still in the process of deciding
which way to release it. Should I
release it all at the end
in the form of a proper
physical and ebook
or should I continue doing it one step
at a time? Let me decide and I'll get
back to you all.
But, thank you for reminding me, Amisha
ji.
Suresh
is a new member. Well, thank you very
much, Suresh ji. I really appreciate you
becoming a member and I welcome you
to the channel. Thank you so much. I
appreciate your support, sir.
W
B R says, "Was magnificent Nehru
comparable to Clinton or Trump?"
Well,
>> [laughter]
>> well, certain aspects were
similarly magnificent.
Certain aspects of Shri Nehru ji's
personality, of his multifaceted
personality, were
potentially reminiscent of Shri
uh Bill Clinton ji or Shri Donald Trump
ji. Certain aspects.
You see, Mr. Nehru was a very
very charismatic person.
He was very popular apparently with the
ladies. So, these aspects seem to
>> [laughter]
>> uh
kind of comparable.
Apart from that, I don't know.
Okay.
Om Sushant Bharadwaj says, "I pulled
that code of life and
time from your book.
Honestly, it's a great read."
Okay. Okay. Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, that's why it
echoed
what I said. Well, thank you very much
for pointing that out and I once again
completely agree with what you said.
Thank you, ji.
Uh Lakshman Tahiliani says, "How much
time does India have to sort Pakistan
out?"
Um how much time does India have
to sort Pakistan out? That's a good
question.
6 months, 1 year?
The longer we take to sort them out,
the more of a price we may have to pay.
I would say 6 months to 1 year.
Maximum 3 years. I would I would say 3
years is too late.
That's why I said earlier in this uh
episode, right?
I foresee a war between India and
Pakistan in the next 1 to 3 years.
I would say 6 months to 1 year we have
to sort them out, otherwise it'll be too
late.
Galuwer says,
"Om Sushant Bharadwaj, I think quoted
Nila
Nityanand's DIL." Okay, I'm not sure.
This is a conversation with somebody
else. All right. Okay.
Um
Okay, it's it's to me, is it?
Okay, I'm a little confused. What is Is
it a question to me?
"I think quoted Nityanand's DIL." What's
a DIL?
Yeah, I'm not sure what you're saying
here, but no questions like this. Okay.
No problem. Thank you.
Um Satellite, I'm not sure what that
means, but okay. Satellite says, "Next
Ask Me Anything livestream, ask some
questions."
Maybe I should do a
generic Ask Me Anything livestream
in which I take questions about
anything.
Sure, I I can do that.
How about next weekend I do an Ask Me
Abhijit livestream, which will be a
general livestream, not specifically
geopolitics. Sure. Okay, done.
This coming Sunday. Let me make a mental
note of that. This coming Sunday, it
will be a
a freestyle livestream. No specific
topic. All right, I'll do that. Thank
you for the suggestion.
Uh Kirtan Gupta doesn't have a question.
No problem, sir. Thank you very much for
your contribution. Thank you, sir.
The Scummer says, "Why don't we fence
all our borders?" Well, the problem with
fencing all our borders is is that you
can't fence borders that are like 7 km
high, right? Or 5 km high across
mountainous terrain, glaciers, ice.
Sometimes you have borders in very hilly
hilly regions.
Up and down, up and down, forests and
waterfalls and whatnot. How do you How
do you fence that?
Sometimes you can't.
If you go to the Himalayas, if you go
there physically and you see the
situation there, see the kind of
mountains we have,
you'll understand it's not possible to
fence the borders there. So, there are
practical reasons why it's not possible
always to fence fence all the borders.
As far as possible, we should.
SK1 says, "Namaste." Namaste and thank
you very much
for your contribution. Thank you so
much.
James says, "There is more racism in
India than than there is in the EU."
You see,
I'm not sure if it's more or less,
but there's no question about
the fact that
there is racism in every nation.
It is there. It's It's a It's a fact of
life. There is some amount of racism in
every nation.
It It It is what it is. It's human
nature.
Can't do anything about it.
But, I'm not sure about India having
more racism than the EU. I'm not sure
about that, James.
Not sure about that.
Have you been to the EU?
You were The UK was a member of the EU,
wasn't it, before Brexit happened?
Brexit.
The Europeans are pretty racist.
I know that for a fact. Depending on
which nation you're in. Certain nations
are super racist. So, I would say
Indians are way less racist actually
than than than the than the average
European. I would say the average Indian
is significantly less racist than the
average European. That is something I
can say
from
firsthand experience.
Uh Indig 3,000 kg of rare earth magnets
enough for ISRO. What is the Indig?
Um
not sure what the question is. 3,000 kg
of rare earth magnets, is it enough?
Indigenous?
Is it enough for ISRO? I'm not sure. I'm
not sure. If If you're asking if 3,000
kg of indigenous rare earth magnets is
it enough for ISRO, I'm not sure because
I'm not sure how ISRO is using rare
earths
or
neodymium magnets or whatever it is
for what purpose. I'm not sure. I can't
I can't answer the question, right?
Shivarally says, "How did we evolve from
apes?"
Well,
not sure how it is connected to
geopolitics, but
we evolved through natural selection.
We evolved through uh the the need to
survive.
And evolution doesn't happen over 2
weeks, right? It happens over hundreds
of thousands of years.
So, [snorts]
it happened over time. The
environmental factors and the pressures
of natural selection and the survival of
the fittest, all these pressures
and the changing environment of of the
earth and the evolving threat scenarios
for humans, all of these things they
shaped our evolution and that's how it
happened.
Um Om Sushant Bharadwaj says, "It is all
related to the book Borrowed Time, the
first book of the Mirrors Mirrors of
Maya."
Got it. Got it. Got it.
Thank you. Thank you once again.
All right. That brings me to the end of
the livestream.
I've taken I suppose all the questions.
Okay, there's one more question
uh from the super chat. "Your opinion of
EU
of the European Union Union is similar
to Eva Flardingerbrook."
Flardingerbrook. Who is Eva
Flardingerbrook? Um not sure who this uh
person lady is, but okay. I'll
maybe I'll check out who this person is
and what uh
her I think it's a her. It's a she. What
her opinions are. I'll check it out. All
right. Thank you very much for letting
me know.
And that brings me to the end of the
super chats.
Yeah, we have almost reached 2 and 1/2
hours, so I think it's a
it's a good time to end, but let me take
one final question by Ayush.
"We are getting a subtle hint. Are we
getting subtle hints of a nuclear Japan?
I earlier made a video on this before.
What's my opinion? How will it change
the geopolitical equation in Southeast
in East Asia?"
I think you could have a nuclear Japan
in the next two to two to three years.
It would be in line with what I said in
in
the earlier video. It would It would
also be in line with what Henry
Kissinger had predicted in the year 2022
or 2023 that you would have a
nuclear-armed Japan in the next 5 years.
So, if that happens, it will be a
significant setback for China.
And I'm I'm sure the Chinese will throw
a big tantrum.
But, what can they do about it? See, it
will significantly change the
geopolitical balance of power
in East Asia. See, Japan is a shadow
nuclear power.
It has the technology. It has the
technological know-how.
If Japan wants, if it is given the
go-ahead by the United States, it can
have indigenous nuclear weapons
next week.
And high-quality nuclear weapons. Japan
is one of the most technologically
advanced nations in the world.
So, they can have it anytime they they
are allowed to.
If this happens, then this will
significantly alter the balance of power
in East Asia.
And I see that happening in the next two
to 3 years.
Perhaps even sooner.
Yeah.
And there's one more super chat, so
let's take this. Assam government using
its special
power
1950 Act that allows Assam to expel
Bangladeshis without any court or
tribunal. Some are now shouting you Some
are now shouting human rights, but what
about mine?
Why are you inside my house in the first
place? What's my opinion?
Okay, I'm not aware of this 1950 Act or
whatever it is, but if Assam is now
preparing to expel illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators,
I would very much welcome that step.
Right? Anybody who is inside India
illegally
has to be
deported, expelled from India. As simple
as that. India is not
a Dharamshala like they say.
Right? Only Indian citizens have the the
right to live in India.
If the Bangladeshis have a problem in
their country, they can
change their country for the better.
This is not their land. We have created
a separate nation for them. They should
be sent back there. So, if this is
happening, I would be very pleased about
it.
All right, people. Let me now end the
live stream. That's And we have now
crossed 2 over 30 minutes.
All right, people. Thank you so much for
all the questions. It was really fun. I
I think that we had some very
interesting and
nice questions today.
And let's continue this in the future
live stream. So, next weekend, next
Sunday, I will do
an Ask Me Abhijit live stream in which I
will take questions about any topic, not
only geopolitics, okay?
And we shall do that.
And okay, we we have some more
questions. One one last question. VSVS
says, "I have actually met someone named
Muhammad Vishnu."
Indonesian, right? Indonesians have the
most fantastic names. They have refused
to give up their Hindu identity, their
you know, pre-Islamic identity, and they
have kind of merged that with the new
Islamic names. So, Muhammad Vishnu is
kind of
That's the kind of name you can find in
Indonesia. I suppose it will it will
offend Muslims as well as Hindus.
But yeah, that's Indonesia for you.
Fantastic nation. All right, people.
Thank you so much for the questions.
Keep learning. Keep asking questions.
Keep raising your standards, and I shall
see you
very soon in the next live stream. Take
care, everybody.
See you soon. Bye-bye.